<?xml version='1.0'?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
<info>
  <title>Rivendell Radio Automation System</title>
  <subtitle>Operations Guide</subtitle>
  <author>
    <personname>
      <firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Gleason</surname>
    </personname>
  </author>
  <publisher>
    <publishername>Paravel Systems LLC</publishername>
    <address>
      <street>41 West Lee Highway, Suite 59</street>
      <city>Warrenton</city>
      <state>VA</state>
      <postcode>20186</postcode>
    </address>
  </publisher>
  <orgname class="corporation">
    
  </orgname>
  <edition>
    v1.0.0
  </edition>
  <copyright><year>-2003-2017</year><holder>Fred Gleason</holder></copyright>
  <cover>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="manual-outputdefault.png" scale="20"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </cover>
</info>
<!--
<preface><title>Forward</title></preface>
-->

<chapter>
  <title>System Overview</title>
<!--
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="manual-outputdefault.png" scale="30"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
-->
  <sect1>
    <title>Introducing Rivendell</title>
    <para>
      Rivendell is a digital audio content management and delivery system
      that is targeted for use in professional radio broadcast environments.
      It includes robust tools for the acquisition, organization, management
      and play out of audio material from and to a diverse array of sources
      and destinations.  Support for a wide variety of external third party
      hardware devices and software packages commonly used in the radio
      industry is featured, including interfaces for:
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>Audio Routing Switchers</listitem>
	<listitem>Satellite Downlink Receivers</listitem>
	<listitem>Audio Mixing Consoles</listitem>
	<listitem>Commercial Traffic and Music Scheduling Systems</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Rivendell is made available under the terms of the GNU General Public
      License version 2 (GPLv2), a copy of which can be found in Appendix A.
      As such, it comes with <emphasis>absolutely no warranty</emphasis>,
      not even the implied
      warranties of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose.
      See the full text of the GPLv2 for details.
    </para>
    <para>
      Rivendell has been designed and developed from the ground up to run
      on the popular and highly stable <trademark>GNU/Linux</trademark>
      operating system.
      Selected tools (mostly having to do with log generation) have also
      been ported to run in the Microsoft <trademark>Windows</trademark>
      environment as well.
      Full source code as well as binary installation packages for Windows
      and select Linux distributions are available on line.  Consult the
      Rivendell Technical and Administration Guide for details.
    </para>
    <para>
      Rivendell has been designed to be able to operate in a wide variety
      of roles, ranging from single, self-contained workstations to large,
      multi-station clusters consisting of multiple workstations and
      centralized servers.  Also included are redundancy and hot-standby
      capabilities to allow for reliable operation even in the presence of
      hardware faults.  Details can be found in the Rivendell Technical
      and Administration Guide.
    </para>
    <para>
      Rivendell is implemented as a set of interactive tools or 'modules'
      that collectively provide the complete functionality of the system.
      Briefly, these modules and their functions are:
    </para>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDAdmin</term>
	  <listitem>
	    System wide configuration
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDLibrary</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Library content management
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDCatch</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Automatic event scheduler
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDAirPlay</term>
	  <listitem>
	    On-air play out application
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDLogEdit</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Log editing and voicetracking tool
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDLogManager</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Automated log generation and interface utility
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDLogin</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Set the current user on a Rivendell host
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDCartSlots</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Emulate a traditional broadcast cart machine
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDPanel</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Large &quot;cart wall&quot; application
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>RDCastManager</term>
	  <listitem>
	    Podcast feed manager
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The operation of each of these modules is explained in detail in the
      chapters that follow.  However, we first need to cover some basic
      concepts common to all Rivendell modules.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Rivendell Security Paradigm</title>
      <para>
	All Rivendell modules make use of the following four classes of
	system resources:
      </para>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    Hosts
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    Users
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    Groups
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    Services
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	We'll cover each of these concepts in turn.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Hosts</title>
	<para>
	  Every physical computer within a given network that is running
	  Rivendell software is referred to as a <emphasis>host</emphasis>.
	  Any host in a
	  Rivendell network can be individually configured and controlled
	  from any other host (provided the system administrator has enabled
	  this capability).  Hosts can be used for a wide variety of
	  applications, including content ingestion and management,
	  automatic recording (sometimes referred to as netcatching),
	  on-air play out or log (sometimes also referred to as playlist)
	  generation.  It is also possible for a single host to perform all
	  of these functions.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Users</title>
	<para>
	  Every host on a Rivendell network has one or more
	  <emphasis>users</emphasis> available
	  to it.  In this context, a 'user' is merely a set of access
	  policies established by the system administrator that defines what
	  tasks a given host is or is not allowed to perform.  Every host
	  has at least one user, called the <emphasis>default user</emphasis>.
	  As the name
	  suggests, this is the set of user policies that are loaded by
	  default when the system starts up.  It is also possible to change
	  the user currently in use on a given host by running the RDLogin
	  module. 
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Groups</title>
	<para>
	  A Rivendell <emphasis>group</emphasis> is a system of categories
	  that is used by the
	  audio library to classify and organize the audio within the library.
	  Groups are a very powerful capability, and many operations within
	  Rivendell can be specified on the basis of group membership.
	  The actual classification scheme, including the number of available
	  groups and their names, is completely arbitrary so as to allow each
	  facility to tailor a schema that best fits its own operational
	  requirements. Designing and implementing the group schema is one
	  of the most important tasks facing the Rivendell system
	  administrator, as a well-designed schema can make long-term
	  maintenance and management of the system substantially easier
	  vis-a-vis a poorly thought out one.  We will cover groups in
	  detail in the chapters devoted to the RDLibrary and RDAdmin modules.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Services</title>
	<para>
	  Every facility at which Rivendell is deployed is presumed to have 
	  one or more ultimate destinations for which audio is intended.
	  These could be radio stations (e.g. WAVA), satellite uplink
	  channels, live Internet audio streams, or any mix of the above.
	  Each of these sorts of destinations is referred to in Rivendell
	  as a <emphasis>service</emphasis>, and certain parameters,
	  particularly as regards
	  audio play out and log (playlist) creation, can be configured on
	  the basis of what particular service is being referenced.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Rivendell Hardware Paradigm</title>
      <para>
	In addition to the core computer hardware (CPU, motherboard, etc),
	each Rivendell host typically interacts with specialized hardware
	required to accomplish the task at hand.  Three main categories of
	such 'special' hardware are of interest to us here, the three being
	audio adapters, serial ports and GPIO/switcher devices.  We'll
	cover each below.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Audio Adapters</title>
	<para>
	  An <emphasis>audio adapter</emphasis> in Rivendell is simply a
	  device or facility for
	  getting audio into and/or out of a host on a realtime basis.
	  Most commonly this will be a sound card, although other, more
	  exotic possibilities (using TCP/IP networking or direct routing
	  to other audio applications) also exist.  The three main classes
	  of audio adapters supported by Rivendell are:
	</para>
	<para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Advanced Linux Sound Architecture (ALSA)</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The standard Linux sound card driver starting with the 2.6.x
		  kernel series, ALSA supports a huge array of commercially
		  available sound cards, ranging from entry level 'game' cards
		  to high-end cards aimed at professional audio uses.
		  More information, including a current list of supported
		  cards, is available at the ALSA web site,
		  http://www.alsa-project.org/.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>HPI Adapters</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  These are high-performance sound cards manufactured by
		  AudioScience Corporation.  Designed and built specifically
		  for broadcast automation applications, many feature advanced
		  capabilities (such as on-board MPEG codecs and AES3 i/o)
		  specially aimed for use in that setting.  They are so-called
		  because Rivendell uses AudioScience's special 'HPI' driver
		  to access and control them.  More information is available
		  at AudioScience's web site, http://www.audioscience.com/.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>JACK Audio Interconnect Kit</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  JACK is not a particular set of hardware devices, but rather
		  an audio 'framework' that allows compliant applications to
		  share audio resources and route audio in realtime amongst
		  themselves.  JACK is different from similar efforts within
		  the Linux realm in that it was designed from the ground up
		  for professional audio work, with particular focus upon
		  low-latency operation and synchronous  execution of all
		  clients.  More information can be found at the JACK web
		  site, http://jackit.sourceforge.net/.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Serial Ports</title>
	<para>
	  Commonly known in the DOS/Windows world as 'COM ports', 
	  <emphasis>serial ports</emphasis> are often used to communicate
	  with outboard gear, such as
	  satellite receivers and audio switchers.  Up to eight serial ports
	  can be accessed simultaneously by each Rivendell host.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>GPIO/Switcher Devices</title>
	<para>
	  Because these capabilities are often (although not always)
	  bundled together in the same device, Rivendell lumps GPIO and
	  switcher devices together within the same class.
	  <emphasis>GPIO</emphasis> stands
	  for 'General Purpose Input Output'.  As the name implies, these
	  devices can be used to interface to a huge variety of outboard
	  equipment by means of control lines. <emphasis>GPI</emphasis>
	  (General Purpose Input)
	  lines can be used to sense changes in an outboard system's state
	  (and Rivendell programmed to take various actions on the basis of
	  that), while <emphasis>GPO</emphasis> (General Purpose Output)
	  lines can be used to
	  send commands to an outboard system.  The actual physical
	  interfacing of GPIO devices is complex and generally beyond
	  the scope of this document.  Readers are encouraged to consult
	  a good handbook on radio engineering for more information. 
	  A current list of GPIO/Switcher devices supported by Rivendell
	  can be found in 'docs/GPIO.txt' file in the Rivendell sources.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Managing the Current User with RDLogin</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>RDLogin</title>
    <para>
      Rivendell uses a sophisticated system of user privileges to keep track
      of which users have permission to perform what operations.
      These privileges are tracked by the system on the basis of
      <emphasis>user accounts</emphasis>.
      Creating user accounts and administering their permissions
      are done in the RDAdmin module and are covered in the Rivendell
      Technical and Administration Guide.
    </para>
    <para>
      It's important to note that these user accounts are not the same
      thing as the “Login Name” that is used to log into the computer system
      itself.  Rather, they exist and have meaning only within the Rivendell
      system.  For the rest of this discussion, when we talk about “users”,
      it is these “Rivendell users” that we are referring to.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each Rivendell host has a default user. As the name implies, this is
      the user that is automatically logged in after the system is booted.
      By default, the name of this user is “user”, but the system
      administrator may have changed this to some other name.
    </para>
    <para>
      For many sites, a single default user is all that is ever required.
      For some sites however, particularly larger ones, it is desirable
      to have multiple user accounts, each tailored to a particular person
      or “role”, with privileges assigned appropriately.  Such sites
      require a means to log different users in and out of the system,
      without interfering with any playout operations that may be ongoing
      at the time.  RDLogin is the module for doing this.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDLogin will display a small window after being started, showing the
      currently logged-in user (see Illustration 1).  To change to a
      different user, select the desired user name from the Username:
      control, enter the correct password, and then touch the Set User
      button.  To “log out” of the system (in reality, just return to the
      default user), simply touch the Default User button (no password is
      required to set the default user).  To exit RDLogin and do nothing,
      simply touch the Cancel button.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Content Management with RDLibrary</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Rivendell Library Structure and RDLibrary</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Carts</title>
      <para>
	The Rivendell Library consists of a set of objects called
	<emphasis>carts</emphasis>.
	A cart is a data container that holds either one or more pieces
	of audio (called an <emphasis>audio cart</emphasis>), or macro
	commands to the system
	(called a <emphasis>macro cart</emphasis>). The cart is the
	fundamental schedule
	building block in Rivendell, in that it is the smallest object or
	'atom' that the outside world (like a traffic or music scheduler)
	can see.
      </para>
      <para>
	RDLibrary, upon startup, will show the current list of all carts
	on the system, as in  Illustration 2 below:
      </para>
      <para>
	A number of important attributes of carts can be seen from this
	illustration.  First is the cart's number.  Each cart in the Library
	gets assigned a unique number when it is created.  This number can
	range between 000001 and 999999, and is the primary 'handle' by which
	both Rivendell and external systems (like traffic or music schedulers)
	refer to the cart.  Very often, sites have specific rules concerning
	which types of audio (commercials, promos, music, etc) and macros get
	assigned which numbers.  We'll cover this area in some detail when
	we discuss groups.
      </para>
      <para>
	Immediately to the left of the cart number is an icon indicating
	the type of cart. Just to the right of the cart number is the
	average length of the cart.  Except in the case of where
	timescaling is in use (in which case it will be indicated in
	blue numerals), this value is calculated automatically by the system.
      </para>
      <para>
	Next comes various columns showing information from the cart
	label – Title, Artist, Client and Agency data, etc.  This
	information can be edited by opening RDLibrary's Edit Cart dialog
	(Illustration 3), either by double-clicking on the desired cart
	entry in the list, or by touching the desired cart entry and then
	touching the Edit button.  In either case, you should get a dialog
	similar to that shown in Illustration 3.
      </para>
      <para>
	This is how an audio cart looks when loaded into the Edit Cart dialog.
	The upper half of the dialog is the cart label data.  The meaning
	of most of these fields should be fairly self-evident, but a few
	call for special comment:
      </para>
      <para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Enforce Length</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		When checked, this indicates that timescaling should be
		applied to this cart when it is played in RDAirPlay,
		meaning that the cart will air at the length indicated by
		the Forced Length field, rather than the native length of
		the audio.  Care is needed when implementing timescaling
		within a facility, as there are limits to how much the
		length can be altered, while only certain types of audio
		adapters support it at all.  See the Rivendell Technical
		Guide for more information.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Group</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This is a pull down menu by which the group ownership for
		the cart can be set.  The system administrator configures
		the list of available groups for each user in RDAdmin.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>User Defined</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		As the name implies, this field has no dedicated meaning
		to Rivendell itself, but is provided for each site to use
		as is seen fit.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>
	The example in Illustration 3 shows an audio cart.  As such, the
	bottom half of the dialog displays the lists of cuts contained
	within the cart.  
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Cuts</title>
      <para>
	Each audio cart can contain one or more <emphasis>cuts</emphasis>.
	A Rivendell cut is
	an actual piece of audio, somewhat analogous to a 'track' on a CD.
	Up to 999 such cuts can exist within a single cart.  Each line in
	the cut list contains information about the cut, including:
      </para>
      <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Description</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      n arbitrary name, assignable by the user as an aid in keeping
	      track of the content, it is roughly analogous to the 'Title'
	      field in the cart label.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Length</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The actual, measured play out length of the cut audio.
	      This field is calculated automatically by the system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Last Played</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      he last date and time that the cut was aired by one of the
	      on-air modules.  Useful for keeping track of stale inventory.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term># Of Plays</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The total number of times the cut has been aired by the
	      one of the on-air modules.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Origin</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The name of the host upon which the audio in the cut was last
	      recorded, along with the date and time.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Outcue</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      A user settable field. This line shows up in the RDAirPlay
	      log when the cut is played.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Multiple Cuts in a Cart</title>
	<para>
	  What happens when more than one cut is placed into a cart? The
	  answer, in a word, is <emphasis>rotation</emphasis>. Rotation is
	  the ability to
	  schedule a single cart in a log, but to have that cart play out
	  different material at different times.  This capability has a
	  myriad of uses.  One of the simplest, common in commercial radio
	  facilities, is to allow multiple versions of a spot to be placed
	  into the system, while still allowing the traffic department to
	  have to track and schedule only one cart number.  A more
	  sophisticated use involves use of the cut's
	  <emphasis>dayparting</emphasis> settings,
	  forcing different cuts to play based upon certain date/time
	  criteria, such as day of the week or time of day. Cut dayparting
	  is a very powerful feature in Rivendell, and is something we
	  will discuss shortly.
	</para>
	<para>
	  To edit the properties of a cut, either double-click its entry
	  in the cut list, or touch it once to highlight and then touch
	  the Cut Info/Record button.  The Record Dialog (Illustration 4)
	  will now open up.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Roughly the upper third of the dialog is for editing the various
	  cut parameters, the middle section is for  configuring the cut's
	  daypart settings, and the bottom third is a record machine that
	  can be used both to record new audio into the system and to
	  audition any recording already made.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Cut Dayparting</title>
	<para>
	  Each cut in Rivendell can be dayparted on the basis of three
	  parameters:
	</para>
	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      Absolute Start and End Date-Time
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      Relative Start and End Time
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      Day of the Week
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	  By default, each newly created cut starts out with dayparting
	  disabled, meaning that it will be 'eligible to play' at all times.
	  By clicking the Enabled button in the Air Date/Time box, an
	  absolute start and end date for the cut can be entered, meaning
	  that the cut will be prevented from airing in the RDAirPlay module
	  at any time outside the range of those date-times.  Likewise, by
	  selecting the  Enabled button in the Daypart box, start and end
	  times (relative to the day the cut is to air) can be entered.
	  Cuts designated in this way will be allowed to air only within
	  the specified range of times.  Finally, by selecting or clearing
	  the appropriate boxes in the Day of the Week box, a cut can be
	  designed to air only on certain days of the week.
	</para>
	<para>
	  All of the dayparting parameters can be used either singly or in
	  combination with each other.  When combined, the resulting
	  'eligibility' is calculated as the logical AND of the applied
	  dayparting limits.  For example, a cut with the 'Monday' box
	  cleared will refuse to air on Mondays, regardless of whether
	  any of the other daypart rules match.
	</para>
	<para>
	  It's important to remember that dayparting rules affect audio
	  play out only within the RDAirPlay module.  You will still be
	  able to audition and play the audio without limitation in the
	  other Rivendell modules.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Cart and Cut Color Coding</title>
	<para>
	  Each cart or cut in RDLibrary is assigned a color to indicate
	  it's 'playability' for air, as follows:
	</para>
	<para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>NO COLOR</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Event will play normally
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>CYAN</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Event will not play (cut datetime is in the future)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>RED</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Event will not play (cut daytime has passed or lack of audio)
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>GREEN</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Event will play an Evergreen
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	</para>
	<para>
	  It's important to remember that the color displayed for each
	  event indicates playability <emphasis>at the instant that the event
	  is being viewed</emphasis>.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Recording and Auditioning a Cut in the Record Dialog</title>
	<para>
	  The lower third of the Record Dialog is used both to audition and
	  record audio.  To audition the cut, simply press the play button
	  (the one with the triangular symbol).  The button should
	  illuminate, audio should show on the bar meter and start playing
	  immediately.  The audio will play to completion, unless either 
	  the stop button (square symbol) is pressed, or the Record Dialog
	  is closed.
	</para>
	<para>
	  To record new material into a cut, first ensure that the Channels
	  drop-down menu is set to record the appropriate number of channels,
	  then touch the record button (round symbol).  If the cut contains
	  audio that was recorded previously, a warning box will pop up at
	  this point to inform you of this and to give you a chance to abort
	  the recording without erasing what was previously recorded.  If
	  Yes is selected here, the previous recording will be overwritten
	  and no longer accessible.  The record button should now be
	  illuminated steadily, while the play button will be flashing,
	  indicating that the record machine is in 'ready' mode.  The bar
	  meter will also be active to indicate input levels, and this is
	  the point where you want to verify that your levels are correct,
	  with peaks just into the yellow area being optimal.  Nothing is
	  actually being recorded just yet.
	</para>
	<para>
	  We have two options for actually starting the record machine.
	  We can start it manually by pressing the play button, at which
	  point the machine will immediately begin recording, or we can set
	  the Record Mode drop-down menu to the VOX (short for voice
	  activated) setting.  When in VOX mode, the record machine will
	  start automatically as soon as it senses the presence of audio
	  at the input.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Once started, recording will continue until either the stop button
	  is pushed, or the maximum allowed length for a manual recording
	  (set by the system administrator) has been reached.  Once stopped,
	  if the AutoTrim drop-down menu has been set to On, the Start and
	  End markers will be automatically set to the beginning and end of
	  detected audio within the cut.  (We will discuss Markers in detail
	  when we get to the section on the Edit Markers dialog).
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Alternative Methods of Audio Ingestion</title>
    <para>
      In addition to manually recording material in realtime, RDLibrary
      supports two alternative methods for audio ingestion:
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  Importing from a File
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  Ripping from a CD
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Importing Audio from a File</title>
      <para>
	To import audio from a file directly into a cut, we start by
	opening the cut's parent cart in the Edit Cart Dialog.  Next,
	touch the cut's entry in the cut list and then touch the
	<computeroutput>Import/Export</computeroutput> button to open the
	Import/Export Audio Dialog (Illustration 5).
      </para>
      <para>
	Select the file you wish to import, either by entering the path
	and filename to it in the <computeroutput>Filename</computeroutput>
	field or by clicking the <computeroutput>Select</computeroutput>
	button to open a file browsing dialog.  Rivendell is capable of
	importing the following types of audio files:
      </para>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    Microsoft WAV (*.wav) – PCM16, PCM24 and MPEG are supported
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    MPEG (*.mp1, *.mp2, *.mp3)
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    OggVorbis (*.ogg)
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    Free Lossless Audio Codec [FLAC] (*.flac)
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	Next, set the <computeroutput>Channels</computeroutput> drop-down
	menu to the appropriate number of
	channels.  You may also wish to adjust the
	<computeroutput>Normalize</computeroutput> or
	<computeroutput>Autotrim</computeroutput>
	controls, although these will normally be set to reasonable default
	values by the system administrator and should seldom have to be
	altered.  If <computeroutput>Normalize</computeroutput> is selected,
	then the imported audio will
	be peak normalized to the level indicated. The
	<computeroutput>Autotrim</computeroutput> does the
	same thing as in the Record Dialog (see section 2.0.1.2, 'Recording
	and Auditioning a Cut in the Record Dialog' above for details).
      </para>
      <para>
	Finally, touch the <computeroutput>Import</computeroutput> button.
	A progress bar will indicate
	percentage completion of the import, followed by a popup box to
	announce completion.  The Import Audio Dialog will automatically
	close after acknowledging completion.  The audio is now imported,
	and can now be auditioned and otherwise processed in the usual way.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Ripping Audio from a CD Track</title>
      <para>
	To rip audio directly off of a CD into a cut, we again start by
	opening the cut's parent cart in the Edit Cart Dialog.  Next,
	select the cut's by touching the cut's entry in the cut list,
	and then touch the <computeroutput>Rip</computeroutput> button to open the Rip CD Dialog
	(Illustration 6).
      </para>
      <para>
	Load a CD into the CD drive.  After a few seconds, list of tracks
	should appear in the Tracks area.  If the system administrator has
	enabled the FreeDB CD Lookup Service, the names of the various
	tracks may appear as well.  
      </para>
      <para>
	Set the <computeroutput>Channels</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>Normalize</computeroutput> and 
	<computeroutput>Autotrim</computeroutput> controls appropriately (see
	section 2.1.0 for more details on using the
	<computeroutput>Normalize</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Autotrim</computeroutput>
	controls).  Next, touch the track you wish to rip and then press
	the <computeroutput>Rip Track</computeroutput> button. The track will
	now be ripped into the cut,
	with a progress bar keeping you informed of progress.  When the
	rip is complete, a message box will pop up to inform you of this.
      </para>
      <para>
	If FreeDB data was found for the CD, you can have the FreeDB track,
	artist and album names be automatically placed on the cart label
	for the cart by checking
	<computeroutput>Apply FreeDB Values to Cart</computeroutput> before
	closing the Dialog.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Ripping Multiple CD Tracks at a Time</title>
      <para>
	Sometimes, when transferring multiple audio tracks from CD,
	it's more convenient to be able to set up the entire transfer at
	once and then let the rip run in a 'batch' mode. RDLibrary is
	capable of ripping audio in this manner as well. To do this, click
	the <computeroutput>Rip CD</computeroutput> button near the bottom of
	the main RDLibrary screen,
	bringing up the Rip Disk Dialog (Illustration 7).
      </para>
      <para>
	This dialog is similar in many ways to the Rip CD Dialog described
	above, except that each track can be assigned to transfer to a
	different cut by double clicking on its listing, or by touching
	the listing and then the Set Cut button, bringing up the Select
	Cut Dialog (see Illustration 8).
      </para>
      <para>
	The destination cut is selected by first choosing the cart from the
	left-hand pane, followed by the desired cut within that cart on the
	right-hand pane.  The complete set of library filtering tools are
	available to you here – see section 2.2, 'Navigating the Audio
	Library' for details on their function, just as in the main
	RDLibrary screen.
      </para>
      <para>
	Once all of the desired tracks have been assigned to cuts, be sure
	that the <computeroutput>Normalize</computeroutput>, 
	<computeroutput>Autotrim</computeroutput>, 
	<computeroutput>Channels</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Apply FreeDB Values to Cart</computeroutput>
	controls have been set as desired, then click the
	<computeroutput>Rip Disk</computeroutput>
	button.  A set of progress bars will keep you informed of the
	progress of each track, as well as overall progress.  When, the
	rip is finished, a message box will let you know.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Macro Carts</title>
    <para>
      A macro cart is a cart that contains one or more commands written in
      Rivendell Macro Language (or 'RML' for short). The Edit Cart dialog
      for a macro cart is similar in many ways to that for an audio cart
      with the exception of the lower half, which contains a list of RML
      commands to be executed rather than a list of cuts (see Illustration
      9). (NOTE: for a complete description of Rivendell Macro Language,
      including a breakdown of available commands, see Chapter Nine).
    </para>
    <para>
      To add a new line of RML, select the desired location in the list
      and touch the <computeroutput>Add button</computeroutput>.
      Similarly, a line can be deleted by
      selecting it and then touching the
      <computeroutput>Delete</computeroutput> button, or modified by
      touching the <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button. The RML
      can be tested, eight line-by-line
      or as a whole by touching the <computeroutput>Run Line</computeroutput>
      or <computeroutput>Run Cart</computeroutput> button
      respectively. It is also possible to
      <computeroutput>Copy</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>Paste</computeroutput> individual
      lines both within a given cart or between carts.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Navigating the Audio Library</title>
    <para>
      The uppermost section of RDLibrary's main window contains tools
      designed to allow for fast searching of the entire audio library,
      making locating a particular piece of audio easy even in a library
      containing thousands of carts.  It's possible to  control what carts
      are listed, as well as how they are sorted.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Changing the Cart Sort Order</title>
      <para>
	The order in which carts are displayed in the cart list can be
	changed by simply clicking on the header of the column by which
	you want them sorted by.  By default, the carts are sorted by Cart
	Number.  To instead sort them alphabetically by Title, simply click
	the <computeroutput>TITLE</computeroutput> header once.
	To sort them by Title in reverse –i.e.
	from 'Z' to 'A' – click the <computeroutput>TITLE</computeroutput>
	header once again.  Clicking the
	<computeroutput>TITLE</computeroutput> header a third time restores
	the sort to normal 'A' to 'Z' again. And so on for all of the columns
	in the cart list – it's
	possible to sort the Library by
	<computeroutput>ARTIST</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>LENGTH</computeroutput>, or any other
	parameter shown in the cart list.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting Carts by the Filter Field</title>
      <para>
	Very often, one will want to find a cart or set of carts whose
	label(s) contains a particular word or phrase.  It's possible to
	narrow the list of displayed carts to this set by simply entering
	the desired word or phrase into the
	<computeroutput>Filter</computeroutput> field at the top of the
	main RDLibrary screen. The full list can be restored by clearing
	the <computeroutput>Filter</computeroutput> field or by clicking
	the Clear button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting Carts by Group</title>
      <para>
	It's possible to limit the list of carts to only those in a
	particular group by setting the <computeroutput>Group</computeroutput>
	drop-down menu to the
	desired group name.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting Carts by Type</title>
      <para>
	You can tell RDLibrary what type of carts to list by checking the
	<computeroutput>Show Audio Carts</computeroutput> and 
	<computeroutput>Show Macro Carts</computeroutput> boxes. Clearing
	both boxes
	obviously results in no carts at all being displayed.
      </para>
      <para>
	It's also possible to combine all four of the above search and
	sorting methods.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting and Opening Carts</title>
      <para>
	Once the desired cart has been located on the cart list, load it
	into the Edit Cart Dialog (Illustration 3) by either double
	clicking its list entry, or by touching its list entry and then
	touching the <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Library Maintenance</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Editing Markers</title>
      <para>
	Rivendell uses a system of cue points within audio cuts, referred
	to as <emphasis>markers</emphasis>. Markers can be used to specify
	a number of
	parameters for a piece of audio.
	Consult <xref linkend="marker_types"/> to see what
	markers are available, their purpose and their corresponding color.
      </para>
      <para>
	Markers are set in the Edit Markers Dialog (see Illustration 10).
	To access the Dialog, open an audio cart, select the cut to open
	on the cut list and then touch the
	<computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button.
      </para>
      <para>
	The Dialog is divided into three areas:  the waveform area in the
	upper half, consisting of the waveform display and
	<computeroutput>Amplitude</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Time</computeroutput> buttons; the transport
	controls area in the center, consisting
	of <computeroutput>Start</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>Pause</computeroutput>, 
	<computeroutput>Stop</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Loop</computeroutput> buttons along with an
	audio meter;
	and the marker button area in the lower third of the window,
	consisting of controls for selecting and positioning markers.  
      </para>
      <para>
	It's possible to 'zoom-in' on the waveform in various ways by
	clicking the <computeroutput>Amplitude</computeroutput>
	and <computeroutput>Time</computeroutput> buttons.
	By default, the waveform
	is displayed fully 'zoomed-out', thus showing the entire length of
	the audio cut.  The <computeroutput>GoTo</computeroutput> buttons
	can be used to jump directly to
	the current play out cursor position, start or end of the waveform.
      </para>
      <para>
	Audio can be played one of two ways:  either by clicking on the
	waveform to indicate where play out should start and then clicking
	the left-hand <computeroutput>Play</computeroutput> button,
	causing play out to start from the
	selected position, or by clicking the right-hand 
	<computeroutput>Play</computeroutput> button, which
	will cause play out to start from the Start Marker (just as it
	would in RDAirPlay).  Clicking the
	<computeroutput>Pause</computeroutput> button while playing will
	cause audio to stop and the play out cursor (a thin vertical black
	line in the waveform area) to freeze at its current position, while
	pressing the <computeroutput>Stop</computeroutput> button will stop
	the audio while resetting the
	play out cursor to the position it was in when
	<computeroutput>Play</computeroutput> was started.
	Clicking the <computeroutput>Loop</computeroutput> button will
	cause the audio to play out
	continuously, looping from end back to start, until either the
	<computeroutput>Stop</computeroutput>, 
	<computeroutput>Pause</computeroutput>, 
	<computeroutput>Save</computeroutput> or
	<computeroutput>Cancel</computeroutput> buttons are clicked.
      </para>
      <para>
	To set a marker, click on the corresponding marker button and then
	left-click on the waveform area to indicate where on the audio
	the marker should be placed.  (NOTE:  With the exception of the
	FadeUp and FadeDown markers, all markers in Rivendell are assigned
	in pairs. For example, placing a TalkStart marker will also cause
	a TalkEnd marker to be placed.)  Markers that have already been
	placed can be moved by selecting the appropriate marker button and
	then dragging the marker to the desired location.  It's also possible
	to specify the position of a marker in the form of hh:mm:ss.s
	(relative to time after the Start marker) by entering the desired
	value next to a selected marker button.  It is also possible to
	remove a set of markers that have already been placed, either by
	accessing the marker menu by doing a right-click on the waveform
	display, or by touching the
	<computeroutput>Remove Marker</computeroutput> button and then touch
	the marker button corresponding to the marker to be removed.
	(NOTE: the exceptions to this are the Start / End markers, which
	are always present and hence cannot be removed.)
      </para>
      <table xml:id="marker_types" frame="all">
	<title>Rivendell Marker Types</title>
	<tgroup cols="3" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colname="Marker Type" />
	  <colspec colname="Function" />
	  <colspec colname="Color" />
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Marker Type
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Function
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Color
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Start / Stop
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Indicates start and end points of audio.
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		RED
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		TalkStart / Talk Stop
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Indicates point to start and stop the Talk Counter in RDAirPlay.
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		BLUE
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		SegueStart / SegueEnd
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Indicates the start and end of the audio overlap during
		Segue transitions in RDAirPlay.
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		CYAN
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		HookStart / HookEnd
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Indicates &quot;highlighted&quot; audio, used by button
		panels and RDCartSlots when placed in Hook Mode.
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		VIOLET
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		FadeUp
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Indicates the point at which audio should be faded up to
		full level after starting in RDAirPlay.
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		YELLOW
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		FadeDown
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Indicates the point at which audio should start fading
		down to off before ending in RDAirPlay.
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		YELLOW
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	As an aid for accurately setting the Start and End markers, it's
	possible to use the <computeroutput>Trim Start</computeroutput>
	and <computeroutput>Trim End</computeroutput> buttons to automatically
	set the markers to the first and last instances of the level
	specified by the <computeroutput>Threshold</computeroutput> field,
	respectively.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Copying and Pasting Audio from Cut to Cut</title>
      <para>
	It's possible to make copies of existing an audio cut on the system
	by opening up the cut's parent cart in the Edit Cart Dialog,
	selecting it on the cut list and clicking the
	<computeroutput>Copy</computeroutput> button. To
	paste the copied audio, simply select the desired destination
	cut (within the same cart or a different one) and press
	<computeroutput>Paste</computeroutput>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Generating Library Reports</title>
    <para>
      Various Library reports can be generated by touching the
      <computeroutput>Reports</computeroutput>
      button on the main RDLibrary screen and then selecting the desired
      report and touching the <computeroutput>Generate</computeroutput>
      button. The following reports are available:
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Cart Report</title>
      <para>
	The cart report consists of a list of all selected carts on the
	system, with their attributes.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Cut Report</title>
      <para>
	The cut report consists of a list of all cuts contained by the
	selected carts on the system, with their attributes.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Cart Data Dump (fixed width)</title>
      <para>
	The fixed-width cart data dump is a special type of report that
	consists of column-aligned data elements, one line per cut for the
	selected
	carts on the system.  It is intended for use where a 'dump' of
	available carts in the system is desired for import into an
	external system (such as a music scheduling system).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Cart Data Dump (CSV)</title>
      <para>
	The CSV cart data dump is a special type of report that
	consists of CSV formatted data elements, one line per cut for the
	selected
	carts on the system.  It is intended for use where a 'dump' of
	available carts in the system is desired for import into an
	external system (such as a music scheduling system).
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Automating Tasks with RDCatch</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Choosing the Correct Automation Tool</title>
    <para>
      Rivendell includes two modules specially optimized for performing
      automatic operations: The RDCatch and RDAirPlay modules.  The two
      modules take radically different approaches in how they go about
      organizing and controlling operations, so a few words regarding
      each may be in order here.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDCatch is aimed at executing actions on the basis of a strict
      time-based schedule, referred to as an event list.  Each action
      (which can be a recording, a play out, an up- or download, a macro
      execution or an operation on an audio switcher device) executes on
      the basis of its scheduled time in the event list, independently of
      all other actions.  As such, RDCatch is often best suited for use in
      settings such as network head end operations or 'auxiliary' roles at
      broadcast stations, where the transitions between events are 
      generally not an important part of the presentation.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDAirPlay takes a very different approach, in that most events are
      organized into one or more playlists or logs.  A Rivendell log is a
      list of one or more carts, organized in chronological order.  As the
      name implies, RDAirPlay is optimized for use in situations where the
      transitions between the various program elements are a key part of
      the delivery and presentation of the content, such as in live air
      play environments.
    </para>
    <para>
      Of course, it's entirely possible to use both modules, even together
      on the same machine at the same time – the Linux OS makes for a very
      robust and capable multitasking system.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The RDCatch Main Window</title>
    <para>
      After starting up RDCatch, you should see the main RDCatch window,
      looking something like Illustration 11.  The window consists of four
      areas:  the record / play out decks at the top, the filter areas just
      below the decks, the events list and the audition buttons and other
      buttons at the bottom.  We'll cover each of these in turn.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Record / Play Out Deck Area</title>
      <para>
	If the system administrator has configured one or more RDCatch
	record or play out decks, they will be visible at the top of the
	RDCatch main window.  A record deck is a virtual 'recorder' that
	can be used to make automated recordings, while a play out deck
	can be used to automatically play out audio.   It does not matter
	on which particular host  a particular deck 'resides' – all
	Rivendell decks throughout the system are visible in RDCatch,
	regardless of which host it is run upon.
      </para>
      <para>
	Starting at the left-hand edge of each deck, there is the deck's
	name, consisting of the name of the deck's host machine followed
	by a number and a letter, an 'R' to indicate a record deck and a
	'P' to indicate a play out deck.  Next, for record decks, there is
	a MON button, used to monitor the audio present at the deck input,
	followed by an ABORT button, used to manually stop an event
	running in the deck.  A description of the currently running event
	next appears (this area will be blank if no event is currently
	active), followed by the deck's status, which could be any of the 
	values shown in Table 2.
    </para>
    <table xml:id="rdcatch_event_states" frame="all">
      <title>RDCatch Event States</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	<colspec colname="Status" />
	<colspec colname="Meaning" />
	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      Status
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Meaning
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      IDLE
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is available for events
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      READY
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck has started monitoring audio but the transport is
	      not yet rolling (record decks only).
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      WAITING
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is waiting for a GPI event (record decks only)
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      RECORDING
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is recording (record decks only)
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      PLAYING
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is playing out (play out decks only)
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      OFFLINE
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is configured but not available
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      Finally, each deck has an audio meter on its right-hand end, used
      to verify audio levels in realtime.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Filter Area</title>
      <para>
	Immediately below the decks is the filter area, consisting of the
	Show Only Active Events, Show Only Today's Events and Show DayOfWeek
	controls.  These controls are used to select which events will be
	visible in the events list area immediately below.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Event List</title>
      <para>
	The event list is a system wide list of all events to be executed
	by RDCatch on all of the various hosts on the Rivendell network,
	with each event occupying a single line.  The status of each event
	is indicated by its background color, as shown in Table 3.
      </para>
      <table xml:id="rdcatch_event_colors" frame="all">
	<title>RDCatch Event State Colors</title>
	<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colname="Color" />
	  <colspec colname="Meaning" />
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Color
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Meaning
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		YELLOW
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is next to be executed.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		GREEN
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is active.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		CYAN
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is in the READY state.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		VIOLET
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is in the WAITING state.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		RED/PINK
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is reporting an error.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	Each entry in the event list starts with an icon that indicates
	the type of the event, as shown in Table 4.
      </para>
      <table xml:id="rdcatch_event_icons" frame="all">
	<title>RDCatch Event Icons</title>
	<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colname="Color" />
	  <colspec colname="Meaning" />
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[RECORD_ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Record Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[PLAYOUT ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Play Out Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[SWITCH ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Switch Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[MACRO ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Macro Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[UPLOAD ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Upload Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[DOWNLOAD ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Download Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	Next on each line comes the description (settable by the user) and
	location for the event, the location being the name of the host/deck
	where the event will run.  Then, comes the start and end parameters.
	These time-based parameters come in one of three different forms:
	a hard time, which is simply an absolute time (in twenty-four hour
	'military' format), a length (in HH:MM format, relative to an
	earlier start time), or a GPI start.  The GPI parameters can be
	somewhat involved.  They are specified in the following format:
      </para>
      <para>
	Gpi: &lt;start-time&gt;,&lt;end-time&gt;,&lt;gpi-num&gt;,&lt;wait-time&gt;
      </para>
      <para>
	Where:
      </para>
      <para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;start-time&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The time, in HH:MM:SS format, when RDCatch will start looking
		for a GPI event (also sometimes referred to as the window
		start time).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;end-time&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The time, in HH:MM:SS format, when RDCatch will stop looking
		for a GPI event (also sometime referred to as the window end
		time). 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;gpi-num&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The number of the GPI event to wait for, in the format
		MATRIX:LINE.  We will deal with GPI matrix and line numbers
		in detail when we cover RDAdmin.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;wait-time&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The amount of time to wait, in MM:SS format, between the
		reception of the GPI event and the actual start of the event
		(used only for Start parameters).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>
	For example, the start parameter 'Gpi: 14:00:00,14:05:59,0:1,01:00'
	has a window start time of 14:00:00 [2:00:00 PM], a window end time
	of 14:05:59, looks for a GPI event on line 0:1 and will wait one
	minute [01:00] after receiving the GPI before starting the event.
      </para>
      <para>
	Next come the source and destination fields.  The uses of these will
	vary depending upon what type of event is being listed, but should
	normally be fairly self-evident.  For example, for a record event,
	the source field indicates the audio source from which the recording
	is to be made, while the destination indicates the cat/cut combo to
	which the recording should be made.  Some events may leave one or the
	other of these fields blank.
      </para>
      <para>
	Now come the day of the week fields.  These indicate on which days
	of the week the listed event should be executed, followed by the
	origin field, which is simply a readout of the Origin data of the
	events underlying cut.  There are a number of other fields which
	follow, but these are less important for understanding the
	operation of RDCatch.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Button Area</title>
      <para>
	At the bottom of the main window are various buttons.  On the
	left-hand side, the Add, Edit and Delete buttons are used to manage
	events in the event list.  Clicking the Scroll button  toggles
	RDCatch into and out of 'scroll mode'.  In this mode, the event
	list display will be advanced automatically so as to keep the first
	actively running event centered within the event list area.
      </para>
      <para>
	On the right hand side, in addition to Close, are three audition
	buttons.  These buttons can be used to audition the head and tail
	of each cut referenced by an event, thus making it possible to
	quickly verify that a set of automatic recordings were properly
	executed.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Adding New Events</title>
    <para>
      A new event can be added to the event list by simply clicking the
      Add button to bring up the Add Event Dialog (see Illustration 12).
      Simply clicking the button that correspond to the desired type of
      event will create it.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Automating Recordings</title>
    <para>
      Automated recordings are configured by means of the Edit Recording
      dialog (see Illustration 13), which can be accessed either by clicking
      the Recording button in the Add Event dialog to create a new record
      event or by touching the Edit button to modify an existing event.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The 'Start Parameters' Section</title>
      <para>
	The start parameters of each recording are configured in the
	'Start Parameters' section.  A recording can be programmed to start
	on the basis of the wall clock time, referred to the hard start
	time, or upon reception of a general-purpose input, or GPI event
	originated by a satellite receiver, tone decoder or other external
	device.  Programming a hard start time is merely a matter of
	entering the desired start time, in 24 hour 'military' format.
	Programming a GPI start involves, in addition to entry of the GPI
	parameters themselves (matrix and GPI line numbers) that Window
	Start and Windows End times be entered, that define the 'window'
	during which reception of  the appropriate GPI event will be
	'recognized' by RDCatch.  It is also optionally possible to specify
	a Start Delay between reception of the GPI event and the actual
	start of the recording.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The 'End Parameters' Section</title>
      <para>
	The end parameters of each recording are configured in the
	'End Parameters' section.  A recording can be programmed to end on
	the basis of a hard time, its absolute length or in response to a
	GPI event.  Programming of the Hard Time and Length parameters
	should be fairly self-explanatory, while the parameters needed to
	program a GPI event are similar to those used for the start
	parameters, with the exception of the 'Max Record Length' setting,
	which limits the maximum length of the recording in the event that
	the expected GPI event is never received.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Programming Multiple Recordings in a Single Event</title>
      <para>
	If a record event is configured to use GPI for its start and Length
	or GPI for its end parameter, then it is possible to configure the
	event to make repeated, multiple recordings within a single event
	by checking the 'Allow Multiple Recordings Within This Window' box
	in the 'Start Parameters' section.  This can significantly reduce
	the amount of required record events when capturing material with
	high on-air turnover, such as newscasts or traffic reports.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting a Record Source</title>
      <para>
	If the selected record deck (chosen in the Location drop-down menu
	at the top of the dialog) as been configured to operate with an
	audio switcher device, the appropriate audio input can be chosen
	from the Source drop-down menu.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting a Record Destination</title>
      <para>
	Each programmed recording must have a 'destination', a designated
	Cart/Cut which will hold the audio.  The currently programmed
	destination is shown in the Destination field, and can be changed
	by clicking the Select button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Setting the Active Days for a Recording</title>
      <para>
	A check should be placed next to each day of the week for which a
	recording should be made in the Active Days box.  If no days are
	checked, then no recordings at all will be made. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Record List Management with Event Active and Make OneShot</title>
      <para>
	The record event will be actually executed only if Event Active
	(in the upper left corner of the dialog box) is checked.  By
	clearing this box, it's possible to 'bank' a record event without
	actually having it run, useful for events that are only used
	sporadically.
      </para>
      <para>
	For events that need to be executed only once, the Make OneShot
	box can be checked.  Such an event will execute just once, and
	then automatically delete itself from the event list.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Automating Playouts</title>
    <para>
      Automated playouts are configured by means of the Edit Playout
      dialog (see Illustration 14), which can be accessed either by
      clicking the Playout button in the Add Event dialog to create a new
      record event or by touching the Edit button to modify an existing
      event.  The process of configuring a playout is very similar to that
      for configuring a recording – see the relevant part of Section 3.3,
      'Automating Recordings' above for details.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Automating Uploads/Downloads</title>
    <para>
      It's possible to use RDCatch to automatically upload and download
      material from both local and Internet-based servers.  Automated
      downloads are configured by means of the Edit Download dialog, which
      can be accessed either by clicking the Download button in the Add
      Event dialog (see Illustration 15) to create a new record event or
      by touching the Edit button to modify an existing event.
    </para>
    <para>
      With the exception of the Url, Username and Password controls,
      the process of configuring a download is very similar to that for
      configuring a recording – see the relevant part of Section 3.3,
      'Automating Recordings' above for details.  
    </para>
    <para>
      The Url control is used to specify the Uniform Resource Locater for
      the material to be downloaded.  The following download types are
      supported: http, ftp, smb and file.  The URL field can also include
      wildcard characters that can be used to construct date-based URLs,
      as shown in Table 5.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Username and Password fields are used to indicate the username
      and password required for access to the server referenced in the URL.
      For public web pages and anonymous FTP servers, these fields can be
      left blank.
    </para>
    <para>
      Automated uploads are configured by means of the Edit Upload dialog
      (see Illustration 16), which can be accessed either by clicking the
      Upload button in the Add Event dialog to create a new record event or
      by touching the Edit button to modify an existing event.  The
      following upload types are supported: ftp, smb and file.  As with
      downloads, the URL field can also include wildcard characters that
      can be used to construct date-based URLs, as shown in Table 5.
    </para>
    <para>
      Configuration of an upload event is very similar to that of a download,
      with the addition of the Export Format control.  This is used to set
      what file format should be used for the upload.  Depending upon what
      software encoders have been installed by the system administrator,
      the following export types may be available: 
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  PCM16 Linear (*.wav)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  Free Lossless Audio Codec [FLAC] (*.flac)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  MPEG Layer 2 (*.mp2)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  MPEG Layer 3 (*.mp3)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  OggVorbis (*.ogg)
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The desired upload format and parameters are set by clicking the Set
      button.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Automating Macro Execution</title>
    <para>
      It's possible to configure the automatic execution of a Macro Cart
      by means of the Edit Cart Event dialog (see Illustration 17), which
      can be accessed either by clicking the Macro Cart button in the Add
      Event dialog to create a new Macro Cart event or by touching the
      Edit button to modify an existing event.  The process of configuring
      a macro cart event is very similar to that for configuring a
      recording – see the relevant part of Section 3.3, 'Automating
      Recordings' above for details.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Automating Switcher Operations</title>
    <para>
      It's possible to configure an automatic operation on a switcher
      device by means of the Edit Switcher Event dialog (see Illustration
      18), which can be accessed either by clicking the Switch Event button
      in the Add Event dialog to create a new switch  event or by touching
      the Edit button to modify an existing event.
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to the usual fields, a switch event has Switch Matrix
      (the name of one of the switch matrices associated with the selected
      Location), Switch Input and Switch Output controls.  When executed, a
      switch events causes a take operation to be performed on the specified
      switcher device between the specified input and output.  It is
      possible to specify the input and output either by their alphanumeric
      names (assigned in RDAdmin) or by their absolute numbers.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter>
  <title>Generating and Maintaining Logs with RDLogEdit</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Logs and Log Events</title>
    <para>
      A Rivendell log is a sequence of one or more events to be executed by
      the system, arranged in chronological order.  (This functionality is
      sometimes referred to as a playlist in other automation systems).
      Several different types of events can be included in a log, along
      with parameters governing how and under what circumstances they will
      be executed.
    </para>
    <para>
      Upon startup, RDLogEdit will show the current list of all logs on the
      system, as in Illustration 19.  A number of important attributes of
      logs can be seen from this illustration, the first being the log
      name, with a summary status indicator next to it. The name is an
      alpha-numeric label that is used as a unique “handle” by the system
      to reference each log, and can be up to a maximum of 64 characters
      long.  The status indicator is intended as a quick visual guide as
      to whether a particular log is ready for air (green check mark) or
      not (red ex). 
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes the log's description. This is a free-form alpha-numeric
      label that can be used to record any information that might be useful
      to have appear on the log list (e.g. “This log for Sunday's show, don't
      modify!”).
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes a column showing the owning service.  Each log is owned
      by exactly one service, which determines under what circumstances
      the log can be played and where electronic log reconciliation (ELR)
      data resulting from log playouts is sent (for an overview of
      Rivendell services, see section 1.1.3).
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes three “status indicator” columns (&quot;MUSIC&quot;,
      &quot;TRAFFIC&quot; and &quot;TRACKS&quot;) indicating the log's
      degree of readiness for air.  A red indicator indicates that the
      particular data element is required but currently missing, a green
      indicator indicates an element is required and present, while a
      white indicator indicates that an element is not required.
      Additionally, the “TRACKS” column contains a pair of numbers
      indicating how many completed voice tracks exist in the log versus
      how many total track markers exist (the subject of voice tracks and
      track markers will be covered in more detail below).  When all three
      of these status indicators show either green or white, the summary
      status indicator (at the beginning of the log's entry in the list)
      will show as a green check mark, while a red indicator in any of
      these three fields will show a red ex.  (NOTE: because a log sports
      a red ex does not indicate that the respective log cannot be played.
      It is merely a visual indicator to allow logs to be quickly
      &quot;eyeballed&quot; for completeness).
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes a pair of columns indicating the valid start date and end
      date for the log.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, there is a column indicating the log's origin –i.e. the
      place, date and time it was originally created.
    </para>
    <para>
      A report that lists the available logs on the system can be generated
      by touching the Log Report button.
    </para>
    <para>
      A new log can be created by touching the Add button and entering a
      name, or an existing log inspected and modified by touching its entry
      on the log list and then touching the Edit button, resulting in the
      log being opened in the Edit Log dialog as shown in Illustration 20.
      The Edit Log dialog consists of three parts:  the top section, where
      much of the information shown on the log list can be inspected and
      modified; the middle section, which shows the list of events
      comprising the log, and the bottom section, where buttons for
      modifying and saving the log are located.  Each event in a log can
      be one of several different types, indicated by the icon displayed
      at the start of the line (see Table 6 for a breakdown of the various
      icons).  The following types of events can be incorporated into a
      Rivendell log:
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Audio Carts</title>
      <para>
	The first, and usually most common type of log event is an audio cart.
	As the name implies, audio carts are Library entries that contain
	audio material intended for playout.  Audio carts were covered in
	detail in Chapter Two in the discussion about RDLibrary.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Macro Carts</title>
      <para>
	A macro cart is a cart from the Library that contains one or more
	system commands that can be used to cause the system to take various
	actions.  They were touched upon in Chapter Two in the discussion
	about RDLibrary, and will be discussed in detail in Chapter Seven.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Note Markers</title>
      <para>
	A note marker is an entry in the log that contains text intended to
	be seen by operators and used as a guide or reminder (program coders
	sometimes refer to this sort of functionality as a remark or comment,
	as seen in the REM command used by BASIC programmers).  Note markers
	belong to a class of log events known as meta events because (unlike
	carts, which exist in the Library independently of whether they are
	placed in a log or not), they have no independent existence outside
	of the specific log where they are placed.  A note marker has
	absolutely no effect on the execution of a log other than to simply
	display some text at a specified point in a log, and as such can be
	useful as a mechanism for making notes or reminders to oneself or
	to others who may be executing the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Track Markers</title>
      <para>
	A track marker is another meta event that is very similar in operation
	to note markers, with one key addition:  track markers designate or
	&quot;bookmark&quot; a place in the log where a voice track is to be
	recorded.  (The entire topic of voice tracks and tracking will be
	covered in detail in Chapter Eight).  As with note markers, track
	markers have absolutely no effect on the execution of a log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Chain Events</title>
      <para>
	Each event in a log has a transition type, shown in the &quot;TRANS&quot;
	column of the Edit Log dialog.  The transition type determines what
	happens when one event in a log ends and the next starts. Three basic
	transition types can exist in a Rivendell log:  PLAY, SEGUE and STOP.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Import Links</title>
      <para>
	An import link is a placeholder event that shows where events imported
	from the external music or traffic scheduling system will eventually
	go. They will be covered in detail in the chapter on RDLogManager.
      </para>
      <para>
	Each event in a Rivendell log can have its parameters modified by
	touching its entry in the Edit Log dialog and then clicking the Edit
	button, thus opening up the Edit Log Entry dialog, shown in
	Illustration 21 for a cart event, or Illustration 22 for a meta event.  
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Event Transitions</title>
    <para>
      Each event in a log has a transition type, shown in the &quot;TRANS&quot;
      column of the Edit Log dialog.  The transition type determines what
      happens when one event in a log ends and the next starts.  Three basic
      transition types can exist in a Rivendell log:  PLAY, SEGUE and STOP.
    </para>
    <table xml:id="rdlogedit_event_type_icons" frame="all">
      <title>Log Event Type Icons</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	<colspec colname="Icon" />
	<colspec colname="Meaning" />
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [AUDIO_ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Audio Cart
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [TRACK AUDIO ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Voice Track Audio Cart
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [MACRO ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Macro Cart
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [NOTE ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Note Marker
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [TRACK ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Track Marker
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [CHAINTO ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Chain Event
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [MUSICLINK ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Music Import Link
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      [TRAFFICLINK ICON]
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Traffic Import Link
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <sect2>
      <title>The PLAY Transition</title>
      <para>
	If an event has a PLAY transition, then it will begin playing when
	the previous event has finished.  PLAY transitions are used when
	automatic event sequencing is desired with no audio overlap (such
	as when playing two voice-only announcements back-to-back).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The SEGUE Transition</title>
      <para>
	SEGUE transitions are similar to PLAY transitions, with one key
	difference:  if the finishing event contains segue data (either from
	the Library or from a custom transition programmed in the voice
	tracker), then the event will start before the prior event is
	finished, causing the two pieces of audio to overlap and mix together.
	SEGUE transitions can be a very powerful tool for creating a variety
	of special effects, particularly when used in conjunction with
	musical material.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The STOP Transition</title>
      <para>
	As the name implies, STOP transitions cause execution of the log to
	be suspended prior to execution of the event. This is often the
	desired behavior in situations where the log playout needs to be
	synchronized to one or more external audio sources (such as remote
	satellite feeds), and is commonly used in conjunction with Hard
	Timed events (see below).
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Time and Time Types</title>
    <para>
      All Rivendell log events have an associated time type, which controls
      what effect (if any) the passage of time will have on the event.
      There are two basic time types:  relative and hard.  Additionally,
      the hard time type has several additional options that further modify
      its behavior.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Relative Time Type</title>
      <para>
	The default time type for log events, a relative time type simply
	means that the event is assumed to have a start time of whenever
	the previous event ends (if it has a PLAY or SEGUE transition)
	or whenever it is started (if it has a STOP transition).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Hard Time Type</title>
      <para>
	A hard time type causes the event to be executed or otherwise acted
	upon when the wall clock equals the time associated with the event.
	Hard times are a powerful feature that can be used to synchronize
	the log to various external events.  An event can be assigned a
	hard time by clicking the Start at check box in the Edit Log Entry
	and filling in the desired time, and will show up with the letter
	'T' appearing at the beginning of its listed time in the
	&quot;TIME&quot; column of the Edit Log dialog. An event which has
	been assigned a hard time can also be set to be a Post Point by
	checking the Make Post Point check box (the concept of post points
	will be discussed in detail in the chapter covering RDAirPlay).
      </para>
      <para>
	The specific action that is performed when the time matches is
	determined by the option parameters supplied as part of the event.
	Three basic actions are possible:
      </para>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    Start the event immediately
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    Cue to the event (&quot;Make Next&quot;)
	  </listitem>1
	  <listitem>
	    Wait up to N Seconds, then start the event
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Start Immediately</title>
	<para>
	  As implied by the name, if the event is set to start immediately,
	  it will be started as soon as the hard time is reached. Any
	  currently playing events in the log will be stopped down.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Cue to the Event (&quot;Make Next&quot;)</title>
	<para>
	  If set to 'Make Next', the event will be cued up to become the
	  next event to be executed in the log, bypassing any intervening
	  events in the log between the currently playing event and the
	  hard timed one.  Any currently playing events are unaffected.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Wait up to N Seconds, then start the event</title>
	<para>
	  Very similar to &quot;start immediately&quot;, with the
	  difference that, if one or more events are currently playing,
	  the log will wait up to the specified number of seconds
	  before stopping them and starting the new event.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Editing Log Event Parameters</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Specifying a Cart</title>
      <para>
	The cart number to use for an event can be specified by touching
	the Select Cart button in the Edit Log Entry dialog, which will
	open up the Select Cart dialog, as shown in Illustration 23.
	Alternatively, it is possible to simply enter the cart number in
	the Cart field if the number is already known.  The Title and
	Artist information will be automatically supplied by the system
	from the cart's label.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Specifying Meta Event Parameters</title>
      <para>
	Note marker and track marker events each take only a single
	parameter:  a Comment text that will show up on the log entry.
	In the case of a chain event, the name of the log to chain to must
	be supplied in the Log Name field, or the Select button can be
	touched to bring up the Select Log dialog to allow a name to picked
	from a list of all those available.  Note that meta events are
	assigned transition and time types just the same as cart events.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Rearranging Log EventsRearranging Log Events</title>
      <para>
	Existing events in a log can be cut, copied, pasted or rearranged
	by touching the appropriate buttons in the Edit Log dialog.
	In addition, touch the Delete button will cause the selected
	log event(s) to be removed from the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Saving or Abandoning Changes to a Log</title>
      <para>
	Any changes made to a log can be saved by touching either the Save
	or OK buttons in the Edit Log dialog.  The current log can be saved
	under a different name by touching the Save As button, while
	touching Cancel will abandon any changes made since the last save.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Missing/Invalid Cart Events</title>
      <para>
	If a given event has a problem (such as referencing a cart that
	does not exist in the Library, or that is not enabled for play on
	the log's owning service) its entry will be highlighted either
	RED (indicating a missing/invalid cart) or MAGENTA (indicating a
	cart without permission to run on the owning service).  It's also
	possible to generate an   exception report summarizing problem cart
	entries by touching the Check Log button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Generating Log Reports</title>
    <para>
      Various Log reports can be generated by touching the Reports button
      on the Edit Log dialog and then selecting the desired report and
      touching the Generate button.  The following reports are available:
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Log Listing</title>
      <para>
	A chronological listing of all events in the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Log Exception Report</title>
      <para>
	A list of missing/unplayable carts referenced in the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Auditioning Audio</title>
    <para>
      The audio referenced by an audio event can be sampled in the Edit
      Audio dialog by highlighting the desired event and then touching the
      play button.  No attempt to evaluate the rotation logic of the event
      is made – the audio played is intended solely as a 'sample' to help
      identify the type of material.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Running Logs with RDAirPlay</title>
 <sect1>
   <title>Overview</title>
   <para>
     RDAirPlay is the Rivendell module used to run logs generated by the
     RDLogEdit or RDLogManager (for an overview of Rivendell logs, see
     Chapter Four).  It contains a wide array of features for enabling
     playout of audio content in live assist as well as fully automated
     environments.
   </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
   <title>Log Machines</title>
   <para>
     Fundamental to the operation of RDAirPlay is the concept of a log
     machine.  A log machine is a virtual “device” into which a Rivendell
     log may be loaded and executed.  RDAirPlay has three such log machines,
     called Main Log, Aux 1 Log and Aux 2 Log.  Each of these log machines
     is completely independent of the others in the sense that different
     logs can be loaded and executed simultaneously in the respective
     machines.
   </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
   <title>Layout</title>
   <para>
     As shown in Illustration 24, the RDAirPlay main screen consists of
     four primary areas:  the top area, which contains a variety of
     indicators for use in live assist situations as well as a set of
     audio meters; the button widget, which occupies the bulk of the
     left-hand side of the screen; the right-hand side, which displays
     either a SoundPanel array or a full log width; and the edit buttons
     in the lower left-hand corner of the screen.
   </para>
   <para>
     The top area contains the following indicators:
   </para>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Wall Clock</title>
     <para>
       In the upper left-hand corner is wall clock indicator, which indicates
       the current system date and time.  The style used for displaying times
       throughout RDAirPlay can be toggled between 24 hour “military” format
       and the traditional “AM/PM” presentation by clicking once on this
       display.  If the system administrator has enabled it, this display
       will also flash RED to indicate possible clock inaccuracy due to loss
       of master clock synchronization.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Post Point Counter</title>
     <para>
       Immediately to the right of the wall clock is the Post Point Counter.
       A post point is an attribute applied to a log event with a hard time
       type.  The post point counter uses this information to display
       countdown and timing information.
     </para>
     <para>
       The counter can be in one of four possible states:  Idle, On Time,
       Under Time or Over Time.  If the next upcoming hard timed event does
       not have its post point attribute set, then the counter will be in Idle
       mode (see Illustration 26).  If the attribute is set however, then the
       counter will provide an estimate of how “on-time” the log currently
       is, on the basis of the current time and events still scheduled to be
       played.
     </para>
     <para>
       If the playout is such that the post point will be reached within one
       second of its programmed time, then the counter will be in On Time mode
       (see Illustration 27).  The value shown in the square brackets is the
       scheduled time of the point point.
     </para>
     <para>
       If the playout is such that the post point will be reached one second
       or more before its programmed time, then the counter will be in Early
       mode (see Illustration 28).  It will also give an indication of how
       much more material would need to be added to make the join on time.
     </para>
     <para>
       If the playout is such that the post point will be reached one second
       or more after its programmed time, then the counter will be in Late
       mode (see Illustration 29).  It will also give an indication of how
       much material would need to be removed to make the join on time.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Audio Meter</title>
     <para>
       Immediately beneath the wall clock and post point counter is the audio
       meter.  The meter shows the current peak levels of audio being played
       out of RDAirPlay, with '0' level referenced to -16 dBFS.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Pie Wedge Widget</title>
     <para>
       In the top center of the top area is the pie wedge widget.  This
       widget counts down the final few seconds of each event.  The length
       of time it counts down, along with whether it counts to the start
       of the next transition or the absolute end of the event are both
       configurable in RDADmin.  The color of the band that grows as the
       countdown progresses (shown RED in Illustration 31) will change color
       to indicate if the currently playing event is the last event before
       a log stopdown.  If it is the last, it will be RED, if not, GREEN.
       A BLUE band and countdown will also appear to indicate the event's
       talk time (if talk time markers have been set in the underlying cart).
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Next Stop Counter</title>
     <para>
       Immediately to the right of the pie wedge widget is the next stop
       counter.  The large numerals indicate the predicted interval of time
       before the next stopdown of the Main Log machine, with the actual
       predicted time in the square brackets.  If the Main Log is already
       stopped, then the counter simply displays 'Stopped'.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Mode Indicator</title>
     <para>
       In the upper right-hand corner of the top area is the mode indicator,
       showing the current automation mode of the log machines. Three
       different modes are possible:  Automatic, in which all log features,
       including PLAY and SEGUE transitions and hard times are fully
       enabled; LiveAssist, in which no automatic transitions or hard start
       times are executed but automatic crossfades are done between
       elements; and Manual, which is very similar to LiveAssist except
       that not even automatic crossfades are enabled (thus permitting
       fully manual crossfade control by means of an external console).
       To change RDAirPlay to a different mode, simply touch the mode
       indicator until the desired mode is indicated.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Label Area</title>
     <para>
       Immediately below the next stop counter and mode indicator is the
       label area.  Text messages can be made to appear here (by means of
       RML commands) to signal the operator concerning the state of the
       system or need to take some kind of action.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Right-Hand Side</title>
     <para>
       Directly below the label area is the right-hand side. The right-hand
       side can display either a  SoundPanel array or a full log widget for
       each of the three log machines, selected by clicking the appropriate
       button in the lower right-hand corner of the screen. (NOTE:
       depending upon how the system administrator has configured the
       system, not all of the log machine buttons may be visible on your
       system).
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Full Log Widget</title>
     <para>
       As the name implies, the full log widget can be used to view the
       contents of a log over its entire length.  To load a log, touch the
       Select Log button to bring up the Select Log dialog, select the
       desired log from the list and then touch Load.  The currently loaded
       log can also be saved by touching the Save or Save As buttons, or
       the current log unloaded by touching Unload.  See Illustration 36.
     </para>
     <para>
       Once a log is loaded, it can be started at any point by touching an
       event and then pressing the Play button.  Any playing event can
       likewise be stopped by touching in the event and then pressing the
       Stop button.  To cue-up an event so that it is the next to play
       (indicated by the event being the first with a light green
       background), touch the event and then press the Make Next button.
       The play parameters of an event can be modified by touching the event,
       then pressing the Modify button, bringing up the Edit Event dialog
       (see Illustration 37).
     </para>
     <para>
       In addition to having the ability to modify the event's time and
       transition parameters, the Edit Event dialog can be used to audition
       the event's audio in Cue or set the start position of the audio for
       on-air playback (so as to allow a program to be joined
       &quot;in progress&quot;, for example).  To audition the audio,
       simply press the play button.  The slider can be moved to adjust
       where in the audio to audition from.  To set the start position,
       press the Start button and then position the slider where you wish
       the start to be.  The red line on progress display indicates the
       current start position.  Pressing the Start button again returns
       the dialog to Audition mode.
     </para>
     <para>
       When running a log, it is often desirable to have the currently
       playing event always in sight.  To do this, toggle the Scroll
       button on (blue background).
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The Button Log Widget</title>
     <para>
       To the left of the full log widget is the button log widget,
       consisting of a column of seven large buttons adjacent to cart labels.
       This widget provides another, specialized “view” of the Main Log log
       machine.  Specifically, the first seven currently playing and/or
       next events in that log machine will always be visible here. Events
       visible in the button log will be shown in the full log widget as
       having a green background.  Unlike the full log widget, the button
       log is always visible, regardless of which display has been selected
       for the right-hand side.
     </para>
     <para>
       To start an event from the button log, simply touch an event's
       corresponding Start button.  Touching the button of a running event
       will either (depending upon how the system administrator has
       configured RDAirPlay) stop or pause it.  To modify an event's
       parameters (via the Edit Event dialog), simply double-click the
       event's cart label.
     </para>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
   <title>Editing a Log</title>
   <para>
     It is possible to edit the log loaded into any of the three log
     machines by means of the log edit buttons in the lower left-hand corner
     of the screen.
   </para>
   <sect2>
     <title>Adding an Event</title>
     <para>
       To add an event, touch the ADD button to open the Select Cart dialog,
       pick the desired cart and then touch OK.  To place the selected cart
       using the button log widget, simply touch one of the yellow WHERE?
       buttons.  To place it using the full log widget, click the event
       where you wish it to go and then touch the yellow WHERE? button.
       If, after selecting a cart from the Select Cart dialog, you decide
       you don't want to add it after all, simply touch the ADD button again
       to cancel the operation (see Illustration 39).
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Deleting an Event</title>
     <para>
       To delete an event, touch the DEL button, then touch one of the
       violet DELETE buttons in the button log widget, or select an event
       and then touch the violet DELETE button.  To cancel the operation,
       simply touch the DEL button again (see Illustration 40).
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Moving an Event</title>
     <para>
       To move an event, touch the Move button, then touch one of the violet
       MOVE buttons in the button log widget, or select an event and then
       touch the violet MOVE button, then touch one of the yellow TO buttons
       in the button log widget, or select an event and then touch the
       yellow TO button.  To cancel the operation at any stage, simply touch
       the MOVE button again.  It is perfectly permissible to move an event
       between two different log machines.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Copying an Event</title>
     <para>
       To copy an event, touch the Copy button, then touch one of the
       violet COPY buttons in the button log widget, or select an event
       and then touch the violet COPY button, then touch one of the yellow
       TO buttons in the button log widget, or select an event and then
       touch the yellow TO button.  To cancel the operation at any stage,
       simply touch the COPY button again.  It is perfectly permissible to
       copy an event between two different log machines.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>The SoundPanel</title>
     <para>
       The SoundPanel is an array of buttons that appears in the right-hand
       side of RDAirPlay when the Sound Panel button is selected (see
       Illustration 41).  Each button can be associated with a particular
       cart in the Library (either Audio or Macro carts), which is then
       played each time the button is clicked.  The soundpanel is
       particularly useful in live assist situations where it is desired to
       drop in some piece of audio on a live, improvised basis.
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Panel Types</title>
     <para>
       The SoundPanel has multiple panels or “panes” that can scrolled
       through by touching the double-left or double-right arrow buttons.
       Each panel has a designator, (displayed just to the right of the
       arrow keys), consisting of the letter 'U' or 'S' followed by a
       number.  An 'S' indicates that the panel is a 'system' panel,
       meaning that its button assignments will show up in all RDAirPlay
       instances across a given site; while a 'U' indicates a 'user' panel,
       one which is associated with a particular user and that will
       &quot;follow around&quot; that user where ever he logs in in the
       site.  (Depending upon how the system administrator has configured
       RDAirPlay, you may not have both of these panel types available to
       you).
     </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
     <title>Programming a SoundPanel Button</title>
     <para>
       To associate a cart with a panel button, first touch the Setup
       button, which will begin to flash.  (Depending upon how the system
       administrator has configured RDAirPlay, the Setup button may be
       disabled).  Next, touch the button you wish to program, opening the
       Edit Button dialog (see Illustration 41).
     </para>
     <para>
       Touch the Set Cart button to open the Select Cart dialog and pick a
       cart.  To clear the button –i.e. have no cart associated with it –
       touch the Clear button.  To assign a custom background color to the
       button, touch the Set Color button.  A custom label can be entered
       in the Label field, or the name of the cart will be used by default.
       Touch the OK button when done.  When done programming all the
       desired buttons, touch the Setup button again to toggle off Setup
       mode.
     </para>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Generating Logs with RDLogManager</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      RDLogManager is a tool for generating Rivendell logs. It is different
      from RDLogEdit in that, instead of building logs line-by-line,
      it allows log structures to be defined by a series of rules (called
      events and clocks) that are then plugged into a time framework
      (called a grid).  This grid is then used to automatically generate
      logs on an as-needed basis.  Each Rivendell service has its own,
      separately defined grid, thus allowing for separate log generation
      rules for each service.  This system of rules allows for very
      powerful, modular features, including the ability to import and use
      scheduling data from various external third party systems, such as
      music schedulers and traffic and billing systems.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDLogManager also includes facilities for generating reports. Reports
      are data outputs that detail whether certain events aired as
      scheduled, and under what circumstances.  Reports are available in
      various formats.  Some are intended to be read by humans, while
      others are intended for use by other, external software systems as a
      means of reconciling exported schedules.
    </para>
    <para>
      When RDLogManager is started, it displays its main menu (see
      Illustration 42).
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Grids</title>
    <para>
      Each Rivendell service has an RDLogManager grid. To see the list of
      available grids, touch the Edit Grids button to open the Log Grids
      dialog (see Illustration 43).
    </para>
    <para>
      To open a particular grid, select its service name and touch the Edit
      button (see Illustration 44).
    </para>
    <para>
      Each grid has slots for every hour of every day of the broadcast week
      – 168 slots in all.  By specifying a particular clock to go into each
      of these slots, a set of rules that RDLogManager can use to generate
      a log for any given day of the week is built up.  To specify a clock,
      simply touch the particular hour of interest to open up the Select
      Log Clock dialog (see Illustration 45).
    </para>
    <para>
      Click the desired clock, then touch the OK button.  To clear the
      assignment of any clock to the selected hour, touch the Clear button,
      then OK.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is possible to 'drill down' directly to the underlying
      configuration of a clock (to be covered shortly) by right-clicking on
      the relevant hour in a grid and selecting Edit Clock.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Clocks</title>
    <para>
      An RDLogManager clock is a collection of RDLogManager events,
      arranged in terms of their start time (relative to the beginning of
      the hour) and length.  It basically can be thought of as the
      &quot;schedule&quot; of an hour – any hour.  Once defined, a clock
      can be plugged into any hour of a grid of any service, thus making
      for easy modularization and changes to a service's schedule.
    </para>
    <para>
      To see the list of available clocks, touch the Edit Clocks button in
      RDLogManager's Main Menu to open the Log Clocks dialog (see
      Illustration 46).  Each RDLogManager clock can be assigned a
      three-letter code and color, as an aid in identifying it when
      assigned to grids.  To add a new clock, touch the Add button, or to
      edit a clock's parameters, click on it and touch the Edit button.
      In each case, the Edit Clock dialog (see Illustration 47) will open.
      Clocks can also be deleted by touching the Delete button or renamed
      by touching the Rename button.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Edit Clock dialog consists of three main sections:  a tabular
      list of events in chronological order, a graphical depiction of the
      clock in the traditional “broadcast clock” format, and a series of
      action buttons across the bottom. The clock's three-letter code is
      set by means of the Code: field in the upper right-hand corner of the
      table area.  Its color can be set by touching the Color button. To
      save the clock without exiting the dialog, touch the Save or Save As
      buttons.  To add a new event to the clock, touch the Add button, or
      to edit an existing entry touch the Edit button.  In either case,
      the Edit Event Assignment dialog will open (see Illustration 48). To
      delete an entry, touch the Delete button.  As in the case of grids,
      it is possible to 'drill down' into the underlying RDLogManager
      event by right-clicking on the respective entry in the clock event
      table and selecting Edit Event.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Edit Event Assignment dialog simply consists of an Event field
      for the name of the RDLogManager event and Start Time: and End Time:
      fields for the start and end times relative to the start of the
      hour.  A list of available events can be brought up by touching the
      Select button to bring up the Log Events dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each clock can be designated as being associated with one or more
      services.  This can make finding the correct clock for a given
      service much faster, as the Filter control on the List Clocks dialog
      can then be used.  To program these associations, touch the Services
      List button in the Edit Clock dialog to bring up the Service
      Associations dialog (see Illustration 49).
    </para>
    <para>
      To designate a service as being valid for this clock, select the
      services name in the Available Services list and then touch the Add
      &gt;&gt; button.  Likewise, to deselect a service, select its name in the
      Enabled Services list and then touch the &lt;&lt; Remove button.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Events</title>
    <para>
      An RDLogManager event is a set of rules that define a series of log
      elements (audio carts, macro carts, markers, etc) that should be
      inserted into a log, along with the appropriate log event parameters
      (transition type, time type, etc) that should be associated with them.
      The actual elements to be inserted can be specified directly within
      the event itself, or imported from a data file generated by an
      external scheduling system.  Up to two such external scheduling
      sources can be defined for each service.  While for convenience sake
      these are designated as 'Traffic' and 'Music' within RDLogManager,
      they can each be used anywhere a means of importing external
      scheduling data into the system is needed, regardless of whether such
      data actually references commercial or musical material or not.
    </para>
    <para>
      To see the list of available RDLogManager events, touch the Edit
      Events button on the RDLogManager Main Menu to open the Log Events
      dialog (see Illustration 50).  It is possible to filter the list of
      available events to only those used for a particular service by
      selecting the service in the Filter: control.  To add a new event,
      touch the Add button, or to edit an event's parameters, click on it
      and touch the Edit button.  In each case, the Edit  Event dialog (see
      Illustration 51) will open.  Events can also be deleted by touching
      the Delete button or renamed by touching the Rename button.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Edit Event dialog consists of two main parts:  a Library cart
      picker widget on the left side, and an area showing the various event
      parameters on the right.  Audio contained within audio carts can be
      sampled by selecting the desired cart and then touching the Play
      button. Programming an event basically consists of specifying four
      things:  its log parameters (transition and time types), the list of
      pre-import events, the event import (if any) and the list of
      post-import events.  The first matter to be decided is if the event
      should have a hard start time:  if so, then the Use hard start time
      box in the TIMED START section should be checked.  Checking this box
      will enable all of the usual hard start parameters to be specified.
      If an automatic timed start is not desired, then it is possible to
      check the Cue to this event box in the PREPOSITION LOG section.
      This will cause RDLogManager to place a hard time with a 'Make Next'
      attribute on the first item of the event – effectively, causing the
      event to be automatically “cued up” at the scheduled time – something
      that can be particularly handy for keeping spot breaks in sync when
      &quot;overscheduling&quot; music.
    </para>
    <para>
      Next, if it is desired to have RDLogManager try to insert
      automatically material from the Autofill List to ensure that the event
      has the length indicated by its parent clock, the Use Autofill box in
      the ENFORCING LENGTH section should be checked.  (Configuring the
      Autofill List is covered in detail in the Rivendell Technical and
      Administration Guide).  If Autofill is enabled, it is also possible
      to check the Warn if fill is under or over box to have RDLogManager
      generate a warning if it was unable to properly fill the event when
      the log was generated.
    </para>
    <para>
      Next, the list of log events (if any) to be inserted before the data
      import should be placed in the PRE-IMPORT CARTS list.  For audio or
      macro carts, these can be simply dragged and dropped from the Library
      cart list on the left-hand side of the dialog.  Meta events can be
      inserted by right-clicking on the list and selecting the desired
      element.  It is also possible to edit or delete elements and set the
      transition type of each element through the right-click menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      The IMPORT section then defines which (if any) source will be used
      for importing external scheduling events into the log.  Either Music,
      Traffic or None can be selected.  If Music or Traffic is selected,
      then RDLogManager will import any events from those sources that fall
      within the start and end times of the event (as supplied by the
      parent clock).  These start and end times can be further broadened by
      means of 'slop factors' entered into the Import carts scheduled
      controls (this is sometimes necessary to get the import to work
      properly with certain external scheduler systems).  The transition
      types to be used for the first and subsequent imported elements can
      be specified with the First cart has a and Imported carts have a
      controls.  If Music has been selected as the import source, it is
      also possible to specify the event to use to import traffic breaks
      embedded in the music log with the Import inline traffic with the
      control.  (Configuration of the actual parser parameters for data
      importation is covered in the Rivendell Technical and Administration
      Guide).
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, the list of log events (if any) to be inserted after the
      data import should be placed in the POST-IMPORT CARTS list.
      Configuration of the events work very similarly to that of the
      PRE-IMPORT CARTS list.
    </para>
    <para>
      The color of the event (as seen in the Edit Clock dialog) can be set
      by touching the Color button.  The list of services for which this
      event is valid can be edited by touching the Services List button.
      To save the event without exiting the dialog, touch the Save or Save
      As buttons.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Generating Logs</title>
    <para>
      After all of the appropriate hours have been populated in a service's
      grid, it's time to start generating logs.  To do this, touch the
      Generate Logs button in RDLogManager's Main Menu to open the Generate
      Log dialog (see Illustration 52).
    </para>
    <para>
      Depending upon how many external scheduling sources are involved,
      generating a log involves one, two or three steps.  Before performing
      any of the steps, it is first necessary to select the relevant
      service for which to generate the log (using the Service: control)
      and the log date (either by entering the date in the Date: control
      or by touching the Select button and picking it off of the calendar).
    </para>
    <para>
      In all cases, a new log is initially generated by touching the Create
      New Log button.  If the log for the selected date and service does not
      already exist, it will be created at this point (becoming visible in
      RDLogEdit).  It the log already exists, it will be overwritten.
      (NOTE: if completed voicetracks exist in the old log, they will be
      deleted when the log is overwritten!)
    </para>
    <para>
      When generating a log, RDLogManager will look for possible problems
      (such as scheduled carts that are missing in the Library) and
      generate an exception report if it finds any.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once generated, the status lights in the Generate Log dialog indicate
      which (if any) additional import data are needed to complete the log.
      Two types of status light exist:  Available, which indicates if the
      required data file is available to RDLogManager, and Merged,
      indicating whether the data has been merged into the log as yet.
      Each light can show one of three different colors:  GREEN, meaning
      &quot;yes&quot;, RED, meaning &quot;no&quot; and WHITE, meaning
      &quot;not required&quot;.
    </para>
    <para>
      For an example, see Illustration 53.  This is showing a log that has
      been generated and has music data available but not yet merged. To
      perform the merge, touch the Merge Music button.  The dialog now
      changes to that shown in Illustration 54, indicating that Music data
      has been merged but that traffic data is still needed.  Once a log
      has reached this state – that of having any necessary music data
      merged – it can be voicetracked without having to wait for traffic
      data to become available.  Traffic data can be merged at any time
      before, during or after the generation of voicetracks.  The actual
      traffic merge is performed by touching the Merge Traffic button,
      resulting in a dialog like that shown in Illustration 55.  (NOTE:
      the configuration of the various data file names and parser parameters
      needed for data import is done in the RDAdmin module and is covered
      in the Rivendell Technical and Administration Guide).
    </para>
    <para>
      It is important to note that the sequence of operations from the
      example above is typical, but may vary depending upon how the system
      administrator has configured RDLogManager at each site.  Some services,
      for example, will have no music data, only traffic, so the music
      indicator lights will be &quot;whited out&quot; accordingly.
    </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
   <title>Generating Reports</title>
   <para>
     A Rivendell report is a data output that details whether certain
     events aired as scheduled, and under what circumstances. Reports are
     available in various formats.  Some are intended to be directly read
     by humans, while others are intended for use by other, external
     software systems as a means of reconciling exported schedules.
   </para>
   <para>
     Rivendell has the ability to filter the data that go into any
     particular report on the basis of the type of material played (traffic
     spots, music or all), the playing service(s) and the originating
     host(s).  The configuration of reports is done in the RDAdmin module
     and is covered in the Rivendell Technical and Administration Guide.
     Once configured however, reports are actually generated by the
     RDLogManager module.
   </para>
   <para>
     To generate a report, touch the Manage Reports button on the
     RDLogManager Main Menu to open the Select Service dialog (see
     Illustration 56).  The dialog will show each service on the system,
     along with the date of the oldest data available for generating
     reports.  Touch the Generate Reports button to open the Select Report
     Dates dialog (see Illustration 57).  The desired report can be
     selected with the Report: control, and the start and end dates of the
     report specified with the Start Date: and End Date: controls,
     respectively (NOTE: not all reports are capable of being generated so
     as to span more than one day). Once the parameters are set, touch the
     Generate Report button to write out the report.
   </para>
   <sect2>
     <title>Purging Old Report Data</title>
     <para>
       Rivendell keeps the raw data used to generate reports indefinitely,
       until manually purged out of the system.  Periodic purging of old
       data is a good idea from the standpoint of minimizing the amount of
       system resources utilized, and can be done by selecting the desired
       service and then touching the Purge Data button in the Select
       Service dialog, opening up a calendar dialog (see Illustration 58).
       Each date that has data eligible for purging will be shown in bold.
       To purge a particular day, select it and the touch the Purge Data
       button.  (NOTE: once purged, no reports can be generated for that
       particular service/date, so be sure that all required reports have
       been produced before purging!)
     </para>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>VoiceTracking</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Voicetracking in Rivendell</title>
    <para>
      Voicetracking is a capability wherein custom &quot;one-off&quot;
      content is created and inserted into logs, making it possible to
      create programming that sounds very spontaneous and &quot;live&quot;.
      In Rivendell, such voicetracks are placed into a special type of audio
      cart known as a voicetrack cart.  These carts are automatically
      created, deleted and managed by the voicetracker interface (part of
      the RDLogEdit module), with no manual user intervention required.
      The voicetracker module also includes extensive capabilities for
      allowing customization of the transitions between log elements.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <para>
	Before beginning voicetracking for a particular service, a
	voicetracker group and pool of available cart numbers must be
	configured in the RDAdmin module.  These procedures are detailed in
	the Rivendell Technical and Administration Guide.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>VoiceTrack Markers</title>
      <para>
	A voicetrack marker is a meta event that can be inserted into a log
	as a &quot;placeholder&quot; to others to indicate where a voicetrack
	is to be recorded. Track markers can be inserted by RDLogEdit,
	RDLogManager events or even embedded in data generated by external
	schedulers.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Using the Voicetrack Interface</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>The VoiceTracker Dialog</title>
      <para>
	To voicetrack a log, start the RDLogEdit module (see Illustration 19),
	highlight the desired log and touch the VoiceTracker button, opening
	the VoiceTracker dialog (see Illustration 59).  This dialog consists
	of three major parts:  the waveform area, the log list and the control
	buttons.
      </para>
      <para>
	The waveform area is in the upper center part of the dialog, and
	consists of four &quot;panes&quot;. The upper three display waveform
	depictions while the fourth contains audition control buttons, an
	audio meter and	various counters.  Directly below this is the log
	list, showing a copy of the currently loaded log.  The control
	buttons occupy the bottom and right-hand edges of the dialog.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Editing Transitions</title>
      <para>
	When an event is selected in the log list, a graphical depiction of
	the transition into that event is loaded into the waveform area.
	If the selected event and its prior event in the log is not a
	voicetrack or track marker, then the selected event will be
	displayed in the third pane of the waveform area and the previous
	event displayed in the first pane.  If the selected event or its
	prior event is a voicetrack or track marker, then voicetrack or
	marker will be displayed in the second pane of the waveform area.
      </para>
      <para>
	Once selected, a transition can be auditioned by touching the play 
	button in the fourth pane of the waveform area.  Play will start
	from the left-hand edge of the topmost waveform.  This start
	location can be adjusted by dragging the topmost waveform to the
	left or right by means of the mouse or touchscreen.  If the
	transition type of the selected event is SEGUE, it is also possible
	to adjust the degree of audio overlap by dragging the second or
	third waveform as well.  It's possible to “undo” changes made in
	the segue overlap by right-clicking on the waveform and selecting
	Undo Segue Changes from the menu.  To make the overlap permanent,
	touch the Save button.  To restore the transition to its default
	state (calculated on the basis of segue markers from the Library)
	touch the Do Over  button.  The transition type can be changed by
	right-clicking on an event and selecting the desired transition
	type from the menu.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Inserting and Deleting Track Markers</title>
      <para>
	It is possible to insert a new voicetrack marker by selecting the
	desired location in the log list and touching the Insert Track
	button. An existing voicetrack marker can likewise by deleted by
	selecting it in the log list and touching the Delete Track button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Moving Between Track Markers</title>
      <para>
	It is possible to move directly to the next or previous voicetrack
	marker simply by touching the Next Track or Previous Track buttons,
	respectively.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Recording a Voicetrack</title>
      <para>
	Once the desired voicetrack marker has been selected, the process
	of recording a voicetrack consists of four steps, each initiated by
	one of the four square control buttons in the upper right-hand
	corner of the dialog.  (See Illustration 50).
      </para>
      <para>
	To begin, touch the topmost Start button.  This will cause the
	audio in the topmost pane to begin playing, with a cursor to show
	playback position (see Illustration 61).  To begin the actual
	recording, touch the Record button (see Illustration 62). To start
	the following event (in the third pane), touch the second Start
	button (see Illustration 63).  Finally, to stop recording, touch
	the Save button (see Illustration 64).  The record process can be
	canceled at any time by touching the Abort button, restoring the 
	transition to its default state. It is also possible to undo a
	completed voicetrack by touching the Do Over button.
      </para>
      <para>
	Once completed, the segue overlaps into and out of a voicetrack can
	be adjusted in the same manner as for simple transitions –i.e. by
	dragging the appropriate waveforms with the mouse.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Adjusting Transition Levels</title>
      <para>
	It is possible to adjust the audio fade levels applied during
	transitions by means of rubber bands on the waveform displays.
	These are green lines with small square targets. To adjust a rubber
	band, use the mouse to grab one of the targets and drag it to the
	desired location.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Importing Voicetracks</title>
      <para>
	In addition to recording in realtime, it's possible to import a
	voicetrack directly from an audio file.  To do so, select the
	desired voicetrack marker and then touch the Import button to open
	the Import/Export Audio dialog (see Illustration 5). (For more
	information on using the Import/Export Audio dialog, see Section 
	3.1.0 Importing Audio from a File). Once imported, the voicetrack
	can be manipulated in the same manner as those that were directly
	recorded.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Hitting the Post</title>
      <para>
	If the event following a voicetrack has its Talk Time markers set,
	it is possible to set the transition so that the end of the
	voicetrack automatically aligns with the end of the Talk Time
	(commonly referred to as hitting the post). To do this, simply
	touch the Hit Post button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Rivendell Macro Langauge</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      Rivendell Macro Language (or RML for short) is a set of commands
      implemented within Rivendell that can be used to program the system
      to take various actions.  A wide variety of commands exist, ranging
      from control of outboard gear (such as switchers and GPIO devices)
      to control of various aspects of log playout in RDAirPlay, to
      Rivendell user management.
    </para>
  </sect1>
<sect1>
  <title>Protocol</title>
  <para>
    The Normal form of a command takes the following syntax:
  </para>
  <para>
    <replaceable>cmd</replaceable> [<replaceable>arg</replaceable>] [<replaceable>...</replaceable>]!
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<replaceable>cmd</replaceable>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  A command mneumonic consisting of  two alpha-numeric characters
	  indicating the action to be performed.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<replaceable>arg</replaceable>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Zero or more arguments, delimited by spaces or, if the last
	  argument, by ! (see below)
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	!
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The ASCII character  33, indicating the end of the command sequence.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Command Delivery</title>
  <para>
    To be executed by a Rivendell system, an appropriate command should be
    delivered to UDP ports 5858 or 5859 on said system, using the SOCK_DGRAM
    connectionless protocol.  Commands delivered to port 5858 may receive a
    reply back to the originating IP address at UDP socket 5860 to indicated
    command success/failure, while commanders delivered to 5859 will be
    processed, but no reply made.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Command Reply</title>
  <para>
    If delivered to UDP port 5858, each command may receive a reply, 
    formulated as follows:
  </para>
  <para>
    <replaceable>rpy</replaceable> <computeroutput>+</computeroutput>|<computeroutput>-</computeroutput>
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<replaceable>rpy</replaceable>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The full command string (including arguments) originally received
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<computeroutput>+</computeroutput>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  ACK response, indicates success of the command.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>
	<computeroutput>-</computeroutput>
      </term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  NAK response, indicates failure of the command.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Specifying Color</title>
  <para>
    In places where a color can be specified as a macro argument, the
    following predefined values are valid:
  </para>
  <simplelist>
    <member><userinput>white</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>red</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>green</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>blue</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>cyan</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>magenta</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>yellow</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>gray</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>lightGray</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>black</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkRed</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkGreen</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkBlue</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkCyan</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkMagenta</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkYellow</userinput></member>
    <member><userinput>darkGray</userinput></member>
  </simplelist>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Binary Data</title>
  <para>
    Certain commands (e.g. <command>SO</command> and <command>UO</command>)
    have the ability to transmit arbitrary binary data in addition to textual
    characters.  Such arbitrary binary data can be specified by means of
    escape codes as follows:
  </para>
  <para>
    <userinput>%</userinput><replaceable>hexcode</replaceable>
  </para>
  <para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>
	  <replaceable>hexcode</replaceable>
	</term>
	<listitem>
	  Two digit numeric value of the byte to send in hexidecimal.
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
  <para>
    For example, the sequence 'TEST' followed by a carriage return/newline
    could be specified as:
  </para>
  <para>
    <userinput>TEST%0D%0A</userinput>
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Commands</title>
  <sect2>
    <title><command>Air Gate [AG]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>AG</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Process an RML only if the On-Air flag is ON.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>AG</userinput>
      <replaceable>rml</replaceable>!
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute RML <replaceable>rml</replaceable> only if the On-Air flag on
      the local machine is ON.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Add Next [PX]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PX</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Insert a cart in a log in the next to play position.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PX
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Insert cart <replaceable>cart</replaceable>> in the next to play
      position on log machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Binary Serial Out [BO]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>BO</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Output a string of binary codes.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>BO
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>hexcode</replaceable>
      <replaceable>..</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Output a string of binary codes represented by
      <replaceable>hexcode</replaceable> <replaceable>..</replaceable> on
      serial port <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>!
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Clear Serial Trap [SC]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SC</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Clear a serial trap.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SC
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>
      <replaceable>string</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SC
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SC
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Clear a serial trap.  The three argument form will clear all traps on
      <replaceable>port</replaceable> that reference
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable> and <replaceable>string</replaceable>.
      The two argument form will clear all traps on
      <replaceable>port</replaceable> that reference
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>, while the one argument form will
      clear all traps on <replaceable>port</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Command Send [CC]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>CC</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Send RML to a remote host.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>CC
      <replaceable>dest</replaceable>
      [<userinput>:</userinput><replaceable>udpport</replaceable>]
      <replaceable>rml</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Send the RML command <replaceable>rml</replaceable> to
      <replaceable>dest</replaceable>.<replaceable>dest</replaceable> may be
      either a Rivendell host name or an IP address.   A UDP port value may be
      optionally specified as <replaceable>udpport</replaceable> (default
      value 5859).
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Connect Jack Ports [JC]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>JC</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Connect a JACK input port to an output port.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>JC
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Attempt to connect JACK input port <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      to <replaceable>output</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Console Label [CL]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>CL</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the label on a control surface.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>CL
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>surface</replaceable>
      <replaceable>chan</replaceable>
      <replaceable>label</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      On matrix <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>, set the input
      <replaceable>chan</replaceable> module label of control surface
      <replaceable>surface</replaceable> to <replaceable>label</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Copy Cut [CP]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcatchd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>CP</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Copy cut audio and metadata.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>CP
      <replaceable>srccart</replaceable>
      <replaceable>srccut</replaceable>
      <replaceable>dstcart</replaceable>
      <replaceable>dstcut</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Copy the audio and metadata from cut number
      <replaceable>srccut</replaceable> in cart
      <replaceable>srccart</replaceable> to cut number
      <replaceable>dstcut</replaceable> in cart
      <replaceable>dstcart</replaceable>.  The destination cart/cut must
      already exist.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Cut Event [CE]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcatchd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>CE</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Place a cut event at the current location of an active RDCatch recording.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>CE
      <replaceable>decknum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>eventnum</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Place a cut event with event number 
      <replaceable>eventnum</replaceable> at the current position of the
      active recording in RDCatch Deck 
      <replaceable>decknum</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Database Backup [DB]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>DB</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Backup the Rivendell database.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>DB
      <replaceable>filename</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Create a backup copy of the active Rivendell database in
      <replaceable>filename</replaceable>. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Disconnect Jack Ports [JD]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>JD</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Disconnect a JACK input port from an output port.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>JD
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Attempt to disconnect JACK input port <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      from <replaceable>output</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Duck Panel Button [PD]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PD</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the duck level of a SoundPanel button in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PD
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      <replaceable>level</replaceable>
      <replaceable>fade</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the duck level of button at <replaceable>column</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>> of panel
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>.
      Panel: <userinput>S1</userinput>...<userinput>S50</userinput> or
      <userinput>U1</userinput>...<userinput>U50</userinput>;
      <userinput>C</userinput> for <replaceable>panel</replaceable> means
      currently selected panel.
      If <replaceable>col</replaceable> and/or <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      is <userinput>0</userinput>: duck all buttons in
      <replaceable>col</replaceable> or <replaceable>row</replaceable>. 
      If playing, the audio fades to <replaceable>level</replaceable>
      (in dbFS) in <replaceable>fade</replaceable> msecs. 
      If specified, only stop carts playing on panel port
      <replaceable>mport</replaceable>. The duck level will be set to 0 after
      the playback is finished, or the button is stopped or reset.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Execute Breakaway [DX]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcartslots</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>DX</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute a breakaway.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>DX
      <replaceable>slot</replaceable><replaceable>len</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute a breakaway of length <replaceable>len</replaceable> (in mS)
      using the autofill carts configured for the service currently loaded
      in the <replaceable>slot</replaceable> slot.  The slot must be in
      Breakaway mode.  If a breakaway is currently executing, it will 
      immediately be aborted and a new one started.  Passing a '0' for
      <replaceable>len</replaceable> will cause any currently executing
      breakaway immediately to be aborted and input audio restored.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Execute Cart [EX]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcatchd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>EX</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute a macro cart.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>EX
      <replaceable>cartnum</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute macro cart <replaceable>cartnum</replaceable> on the local host.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Fire Salvo [FS]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>FS</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute a switcher salvo.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>FS
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>salvo</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Fire salvo number <replaceable>salvo</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>GPI Enable [GE]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>GE</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Enable/disable a GPI line.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>GE
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>type</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>state</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Enable or disable the GPI line of type <replaceable>type</replaceable>
      indicated by <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>.  Possible types are:
    </para>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>I</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Input</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>O</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Output</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>GPI Enable [GE]</command> (old format, deprecated)</title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>GE</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Enable/disable a GPI line.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>GE
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>state</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Enable or disable the GPI line indicated by
      <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>GPI Set [GI]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>GI</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set action in response to a GPIO event.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>GI
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>type</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>state</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute the macro cart <replaceable>cart</replaceable> upon transition
      of the GPIO of type <replaceable>type</replaceable> and line
      <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to <replaceable>state</replaceable>.
      Possible types are: 
    </para>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>I</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Input</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>O</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Output</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>GPI Set [GI]</command> (old format, deprecated)</title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>GI</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set action in response to a GPIO event.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>GI
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>state</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Execute the macro cart <replaceable>cart</replaceable> upon transition
      of the GPIO of line <replaceable>gpinum</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to <replaceable>state</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>GPO Set [GO]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>GO</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the state of a GPIO line.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>GO
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>type</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gponum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>state</replaceable>
      <replaceable>length</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command GPIO line <replaceable>gponum</replaceable> of type 
      <replaceable>type</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>> to <replaceable>state</replaceable>
      for <replaceable>length</replaceable>> mS.  A length of
      <userinput>0</userinput> indicates to hold the state indefinitely.
      Possible types are: 
    </para>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>I</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Input</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>O</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Output</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Possible states are:
    </para>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>0</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>OFF</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>1</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>ON</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><userinput>-1</userinput></term>
	  <listitem>Passthrough hardware input (valid only for Input type)</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>GPO Set [GO]</command> (old format, deprecated)</title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>GO</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the state of a GPIO line.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>GO
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gponum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>state</replaceable>
      <replaceable>length</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command GPIO line <replaceable>gponum</replaceable> on matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>> to <replaceable>state</replaceable>
      for <replaceable>length</replaceable>> mS.  A length of
      <userinput>0</userinput> indicates to hold the state indefinitely.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Insert Serial Trap [SI]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SI</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Insert a serial trap to detect a character sequence.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SI
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>
      <replaceable>string</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Insert a serial trap to execute the macro cart
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable> upon receipt of
      <replaceable>string</replaceable> on serial port
      <replaceable>port</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Label Panel [PC]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PC</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the label of a SoundPanel button in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PC
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      <replaceable>label</replaceable>
      <replaceable>color</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the button at <replaceable>col</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>row</replaceable> of panel <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      to have a text label of <replaceable>label</replaceable> and a
      background color of <replaceable>color</replaceable>.
      Panel: <userinput>S1</userinput>...<userinput>S50</userinput> or
      <userinput>U1</userinput>...<userinput>U50</userinput>;
      <userinput>C</userinput> for <replaceable>panel</replaceable> means
      currently selected panel.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Load Log [LL]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>LL</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load a log into RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>LL
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>logname</replaceable>]
      [<replaceable>startline</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load the log <replaceable>logname</replaceable> in log machine
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>.  After loading, start the log at line
      <replaceable>startline</replaceable> if it is >=0.  If
      <replaceable>startline</replaceable> is -2, the log will be started at
      the first event if that event does not have a 'stop' transition. 
      Default <replaceable>startline</replaceable>=-1. If no 
      <replaceable>log</replaceable>> is specified, the machine's current log
      is unloaded.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Load Panel [PE]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PE</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load a cart into a SoundPanel button in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PE
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load cart <replaceable>cart</replaceable> into the button at
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>,<replaceable>row</replaceable> of panel
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>.
      Panel: <userinput>S1</userinput>...<userinput>S50</userinput> or
      <userinput>U1</userinput>...<userinput>U50</userinput>;
      <userinput>C</userinput> for <replaceable>panel</replaceable> means
      currently selected panel.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Load Slot [DL]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcartslots</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>DL</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load an RDCartSlots slot.
    </para>
    <para>
      This command has two syntaxes, depending upon the mode of the slot.
    </para>
    <para>
      Cart Deck Mode syntax:
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>DL
      <replaceable>slot</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load the cart <replaceable>cart</replaceable> into the
      <replaceable>slot</replaceable> slot.  Passing a '0' for
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable> will cause the slot to be unloaded. 
      This command will be ignored if the slot is currently playing.
    </para>
    <para>
      Breakaway Mode syntax:
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>DL
      <replaceable>slot</replaceable>
      <replaceable>svcname</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the <replaceable>slot</replaceable> slot to use service
      <replaceable>svcname</replaceable>.  Omitting the
      <replaceable>svcname</replaceable> argument will cause the slot to be
      unloaded. This command will be ignored if the slot is currently
      executing a breakaway.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Login [LO]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>LO</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Change the active Rivendell user context.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>LO
      <replaceable>user</replaceable>
      <replaceable>password</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the current Rivendell user to <replaceable>user</replaceable>.
      If no arguments are supplied, log out the station --i.e. revert to the
      default user. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Macro Timer [MT]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>MT</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Timer for running macro carts.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>MT
      <replaceable>timernum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>timeout</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the macro timer <replaceable>timernum</replaceable> to execute macro
      cart <replaceable>cart</replaceable> in
      <replaceable>timeout</replaceable> milliseconds.  Setting
      <replaceable>timeout</replaceable> to <userinput>0</userinput> disables
      the timer.  Sixteen macro timers (numbered 1-16) are available on each
      Rivendell host.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Make Next [MN]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>MN</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load changes to a currently loaded log in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>RL
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      <replaceable>line</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the next event for log machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable> to
      line <replaceable>line</replaceable>>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Message Box [MB]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>MB</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Display a popup message box on a host display.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>MB
      <replaceable>display</replaceable>
      <replaceable>severity</replaceable>
      <replaceable>msg</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Display the text <replaceable>msg</replaceable> in a popup window on X
      display <replaceable>display</replaceable>, with an icon to indicate
      <replaceable>severity</replaceable>.  Valid values of
      <replaceable>severity</replaceable> are:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><userinput>1</userinput></term>
	<listitem>Information</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><userinput>2</userinput></term>
	<listitem>Warning</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><userinput>3</userinput></term>
	<listitem>Critical</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Pause Panel [PU]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PU</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Pause a SoundPanel button in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PU
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Pause the button at <replaceable>col</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>row</replaceable> of panel <replaceable>panel</replaceable>.
      Panel: <userinput>S1</userinput>...<userinput>S50</userinput> or
      <userinput>U1</userinput>...<userinput>U50</userinput>;
      <userinput>C</userinput> for <replaceable>panel</replaceable> means
      currently selected panel.
      If <replaceable>col</replaceable> and/or <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      is <userinput>0</userinput>: pause all playing buttons in
      <replaceable>col</replaceable> or <replaceable>row</replaceable>. 
      If specified, start the playout on panel port
      <replaceable>mport</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Play Panel [PP]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PP</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load a cart into a SoundPanel button in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PP
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]
      [0|1]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Play the button at <replaceable>col</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>row</replaceable> of panel <replaceable>panel</replaceable>.
      Panel: <userinput>S1</userinput>...<userinput>S50</userinput> or
      <userinput>U1</userinput>...<userinput>U50</userinput>;
      <userinput>C</userinput> for <replaceable>panel</replaceable> means
      currently selected panel.
      If <replaceable>col</replaceable> and/or <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      is <userinput>0</userinput>: Start the first loaded button that is not
      active.  If specified, start the playout on panel port
      <replaceable>mport</replaceable>. The started panel will stay active when
      finished, if the 5th argument is <userinput>1</userinput>. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Play Slot [DP]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcartslots</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>DP</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Play an RDCartSlots slot.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>DP
      <replaceable>slot</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Play the cart currently loaded in the <replaceable>slot</replaceable>
      slot.  The slot must be in Cart Deck mode.  This command will be
      ignored if the slot is unloaded or already playing.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Refresh Log [RL]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>RL</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Load changes to a currently loaded log in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>RL
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Refresh the log currently loaded in log machine
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Run Shell Command [RN]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>RN</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Run a shell command.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>RN
      <replaceable>cmd</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Run the shell command <replaceable>cmd</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Select Widget [PW]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PW</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Select right-hand widget in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PW
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Select right-hand widget to log-machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      or <userinput>0</userinput> for sound panel.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Serial Out [SO]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SO</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Output a string on a serial port.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SO
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>data</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Output <replaceable>data</replaceable> on serial port
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>.  <replaceable>data</replaceable> can
      consist of arbitrary binary data as well as textual characters (see
      <command>Binary Data</command> above).
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Serial Reload [SY]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SY</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Reload the configuration for a serial port.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SY
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Reload the configuration for serial port
      <replaceable>portnum</replaceable>.  Normally, this should only be
      issued by RDAdmin following a configuration change.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Set Color Label [LC]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>LC</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Display a color message in the label widget on RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>LC
      <replaceable>color</replaceable>
      <replaceable>string</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Display <replaceable>string</replaceable>> in color 
      <replaceable>color</replaceable> in the message widget. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Set Default Now &amp; Next Cart [SN]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SN</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the default Now &amp; Next cart.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SN
      now</userinput>|<userinput>next
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cart</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the default Now &amp; Next cart for log
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable> to <replaceable>cart</replaceable>.  
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Set Display [SD]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SD</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set a console display.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SD
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>display</replaceable>
      <replaceable>line</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>attr</replaceable>
      <replaceable>label</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      On matrix <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>, set the console display
      <replaceable>display</replaceable> to <replaceable>label</replaceable>,
      starting at position <replaceable>line</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>col</replaceable> and using message attributes
      <replaceable>attr</replaceable>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The message attributes value is constructed as follows:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Bit 7</term>
	<listitem>Display mode</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Bits 6,5</term>
	<listitem>Video attribute</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Bit 2,1,0</term>
	<listitem>Message Text Color</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Display Mode:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>0</term>
	<listitem>Overwrite text</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>1</term>
	<listitem>Insert text</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Video Attribute:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>00</term>
	<listitem>Normal</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>01</term>
	<listitem>Flash</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>02</term>
	<listitem>Reverse</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Text Color:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>000</term>
	<listitem>White</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>001</term>
	<listitem>Red</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>010</term>
	<listitem>Yellow</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>011</term>
	<listitem>Green</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>100</term>
	<listitem>Cyan</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>101</term>
	<listitem>Magenta</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Set Duck Level [MD]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>MD</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set duck level for an RDAirPlay log machine.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>MD
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      <replaceable>level</replaceable>
      <replaceable>fade</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the duck level of <replaceable>mach</replaceable>, or 
      <userinput>0</userinput> for all log machines. If playing, the audio
      fades to <replaceable>level</replaceable> (in dbFS) in
      <replaceable>fade</replaceable> msecs. If specified, only affect carts
      playing on machine port <replaceable>mport</replaceable>.
      Loading or clearing a log will set the duck level back to 0.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Set Label [LB]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>LB</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Display a message in the label widget on RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>LB
      <replaceable>string</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Display <replaceable>string</replaceable>> in the message widget. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Set Mode [PM]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PM</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the mode of an RDAirPlay log machine.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PM
      <replaceable>mode</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mach</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set log machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable> to mode
      <replaceable>mode</replaceable>.  If mode is not given or the Mode
      Control Style is set to 'Unified', then all log machines are set to
      <replaceable>mode</replaceable>.  Valid values for
      <replaceable>mode</replaceable> are:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>1</term>
	  <listitem>LiveAssist</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>2</term>
	  <listitem>Auto</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>3</term>
	  <listitem>Manual</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Sleep [SP]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SP</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Pause for specified time.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SP
      <replaceable>msecs</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Wait for <replaceable>msecs</replaceable> milliseconds.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Start [PL]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PL</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Start a log at a specified line.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PL
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      <replaceable>line</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Start log machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable> at line
      <replaceable>line</replaceable> if stopped, otherwise do nothing.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Start Button [PB]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PB</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Push an RDAirPlay Start button.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PB
      <replaceable>button</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Push button <replaceable>button</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Start Next [PN]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PN</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Start the next event in a log.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PN
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]
      [<replaceable>skip</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Start log machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable>> if stopped, or start
      next event if already running.  If specified, start the playout on
      machine port <replaceable>mport</replaceable>>.  If
      <replaceable>skip</replaceable> is supplied, equal to '1' and the log
      machine is in Manual or Live Assist mode, then any intervening
      meta-events in log between the current 'next' event and the next cart
      will be skipped over.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Start Record Deck [RS]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcatchd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>RS</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Start an RDCatch Recording
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>RS
      <replaceable>decknum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cartnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>cutnum</replaceable>
      <replaceable>maxlen</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Start recording to cut <replaceable>cutnum</replaceable> of cart
      <replaceable>cartnum</replaceable>, using RDCatch record deck
      <replaceable>decknum</replaceable> for a maximum time of
      <replaceable>maxlen</replaceable> mS.  The record parameters used
      (format, sample rate, channels, etc) will be those configured for the
      selected deck in RDAdmin->ManageHosts->RDCatch.  The selected cart and
      cut must already exist.  Any audio previously residing in the selected 
      cart and cut will be overwritten.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Stop [PS]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PS</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop a log in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PS
      <replaceable>mach</replaceable>|<userinput>0</userinput>
      [<replaceable>fade</replaceable>]
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop log machine <replaceable>mach</replaceable>, or
      <userinput>0</userinput> for all log machines. If specified, only stop
      carts playing on machine port <replaceable>mport</replaceable>. If
      specified, fade out <replaceable>fade</replaceable> msecs.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Stop Panel [PT]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdairplay</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>PT</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop a SoundPanel button in RDAirPlay.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>PT
      <replaceable>panel</replaceable>
      <replaceable>col</replaceable>
      <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      [<replaceable>mport</replaceable>]
      [0|1]
      <replaceable>fade</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop the button at <replaceable>col</replaceable>,
      <replaceable>row</replaceable> of panel <replaceable>panel</replaceable>.
      Panel: <userinput>S1</userinput>...<userinput>S50</userinput> or
      <userinput>U1</userinput>...<userinput>U50</userinput>;
      <userinput>C</userinput> for <replaceable>panel</replaceable> means
      currently selected panel.
      If <replaceable>col</replaceable> and/or <replaceable>row</replaceable>
      is <userinput>0</userinput>: stop all playing buttons in
      <replaceable>col</replaceable> or <replaceable>row</replaceable>. 
      If specified, start the playout on panel port
      <replaceable>mport</replaceable>. The stopped panel will stay active when
      finished, if the 5th argument is <userinput>1</userinput>. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Stop Record Deck [RR]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcatchd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>RR</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop an RDCatch Recording
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>RR
      <replaceable>decknum</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop any active recording on RDCatch deck <replaceable>decknum</replaceable>.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Stop Slot [DS]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>rdcartslots</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>DS</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop an RDCartSlots slot.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>DS
      <replaceable>slot</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Stop the cart currently loaded in the <replaceable>slot</replaceable>
      slot.  The slot must be in Cart Deck mode.  This command will be
      ignored if the slot is unloaded or already playing.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Add [SA]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SA</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Add an input to an output.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SA
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command switch matrix number <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to add
      input number <replaceable>input</replaceable> to output number
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>.  Unlike <command>SWITCH TAKE</command>,
      this command leaves any other previously assigned inputs unchanged.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Add With Gain [SG]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SG</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Add an input to an output while specifyng the crosspoint gain.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SG
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>
      <replaceable>gain</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command switch matrix number <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to add
      input number <replaceable>input</replaceable> to output number
      <replaceable>output</replaceable> at gain <replaceable>gain</replaceable>.
      The gain is specified in 1/10 of a dB, with 0 = unity gain. 
      Unlike <command>SWITCH TAKE</command>, this command leaves any other
      previously assigned inputs unchanged.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Crosspoint Gain [SX]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SX</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set crosspoint gain.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SX
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>
      <replaceable>level</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command switch matrix number <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to adjust
      the gain of the crosspoint connecting input
      <replaceable>input</replaceable> to output
      <replaceable>output</replaceable> to <replaceable>level</replaceable> dB.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Level [SL]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SL</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set input gain.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SL
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      <replaceable>level</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command switch matrix number <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to adjust
      the gain of input number <replaceable>input</replaceable> to
      <replaceable>level</replaceable> dB.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Reload [SZ]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SZ</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Reload the configuration for a switch matrix.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SZ
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Reload the configuration for switch matrix
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>.  Normally, this should only be
      issued by RDAdmin following a configuration change.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Remove [SR]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>SR</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Remove an input from an output.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>SR
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command switch matrix number <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to remove
      input number <replaceable>input</replaceable> from output number
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>.  Unlike <command>SWITCH TAKE</command>,
      this command leaves any other previously assigned inputs unchanged.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Switch Take [ST]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>ST</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Exclusively route an input to an output.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>ST
      <replaceable>matrix</replaceable>
      <replaceable>input</replaceable>
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Command switch matrix number <replaceable>matrix</replaceable> to take
      input number <replaceable>input</replaceable> to output number
      <replaceable>output</replaceable>.  "Take" in this context implies
      removing any previously assigned inputs from the referenced output.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>Toggle On Air Flag [TA]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>TA</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the state of the On Air flag.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>TA 0</userinput>|<userinput>1!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Set the On-Air flag to ON [<userinput>1</userinput>] or OFF
      [<userinput>0</userinput>].
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title><command>UDP Out [UO]</command></title>
    <para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Module</term>
	  <listitem><command>ripcd</command><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Mnemonic</term>
	  <listitem><userinput>UO</userinput></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Send data to a UDP port.
    </para>
    <para>
      <userinput>UO
      <replaceable>ipaddr</replaceable>
      <replaceable>udpport</replaceable>
      <replaceable>data</replaceable>!</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>
      Send <replaceable>data</replaceable> in a UDP packet to port
      <replaceable>udpport</replaceable> at <replaceable>ipaddr</replaceable>.
      <replaceable>data</replaceable> can consist of arbitrary binary data as
      well as textual characters (see <command>Binary Data</command> above).
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Interfacing with the Linux Ecosystem:  RMLSend and RDImport</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>RMLSend</title>
    <para>
      RMLSend is a small utility that can be used to send RML commands to a
      local or remote Rivendell host. It can operate in two modes: GUI or
      a command line interface (CLI).
    </para>
    <para>
      If started with no arguments, RMLSend will come up in GUI mode (see
      Illustration 65).
    </para>
    <para>
      The Sent To: should have the name or IP address of the system to which
      to send the RML. Dest: controls the method by which the command will
      be sent. 'RML' is standard RML transmission that returns an echo code
      to indicate success/failure.  'RML (No echo)' does not return an echo
      code, while 'Set Port' allows the destination UDP port to be set
      (useful for controlling Rivendell from outside firewalls). Command:
      is the RML command to be sent, and Response: will show any echo code
      returned from the remote system (or 'No response' if no reply is
      received). Touching the Send Command button actually sends the command.
    </para>
    <para>
      RMLSend also has a full-featured command-line facility that allows
      Rivendell commands to be sent using the standard Linux CLI utilities.
      Consult the <command>rmlsend</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum> man
      page for details.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>RDImport</title>
    <para>
      RDImport is a command-line interface (CLI) program that can be used to
      import audio material into the Rivendell Library. It is particularly
      useful in situations where a large number of audio files need to be
      imported in an automated fashion, and is capable of importing
      thousands of files with a single command-line invocation. Consult
      the <command>rdimport</command><manvolnum>1</manvolnum> man page for
      details.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>The GNU General Public License, Version Two</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE</title>
    <subtitle>Version 2, June 1991</subtitle>
    <para>
      Copyright (C) 1989, 1991 Free Software Foundation, Inc. 59 Temple
      Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of
      this license document, but changing it is not allowed.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Preamble</title>
      <para>
	The licenses for most software are designed to take away your
	freedom to share and change it.  By contrast, the GNU General Public
	License is intended to guarantee your freedom to share and change
	free software--to make sure the software is free for all its users.
	This General Public License applies to most of the Free Software
	Foundation's software and to any other program whose authors commit
	to using it.  (Some other Free Software Foundation software is
	covered by the GNU Library General Public License instead.)
	You can apply it to your programs, too.
      </para>
      <para>
	When we speak of free software, we are referring to freedom, not
	price.  Our General Public Licenses are designed to make sure that
	you have the freedom to distribute copies of free software (and
	charge for this service if you wish), that you receive source code
	or can get it if you want it, that you can change the software or
	use pieces of it in new free programs; and that you know you can do
	these things.
      </para>
      <para>
	To protect your rights, we need to make restrictions that forbid
	anyone to deny you these rights or to ask you to surrender the
	rights.  These restrictions translate to certain responsibilities
	for you if you distribute copies of the software, or if you modify
	it.
      </para>
      <para>
	For example, if you distribute copies of such a program, whether
	gratis or for a fee, you must give the recipients all the rights
	that you have.  You must make sure that they, too, receive or can
	get the source code.  And you must show them these terms so they
	know their rights.
      </para>
      <para>
	We protect your rights with two steps: (1) copyright the software,
	and (2) offer you this license which gives you legal permission to
	copy, distribute and/or modify the software.
      </para>
      <para>
	Also, for each author's protection and ours, we want to make certain
	that everyone understands that there is no warranty for this free
	software.  If the software is modified by someone else and passed
	on, we want its recipients to know that what they have is not the
	original, so that any problems introduced by others will not reflect
	on the original authors' reputations.
      </para>
      <para>
	Finally, any free program is threatened constantly by software
	patents.  We wish to avoid the danger that redistributors of a free
	program will individually obtain patent licenses, in effect making
	the program proprietary.  To prevent this, we have made it clear
	that any patent must be licensed for everyone's free use or not
	licensed at all.
      </para>
      <para>
	The precise terms and conditions for copying, distribution and
	modification follow.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE</title>
      <subtitle>TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR COPYING, DISTRIBUTION AND
      MODIFICATION</subtitle>
      <orderedlist startingnumber="0" numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    This License applies to any program or other work which contains
	    a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it may be
	    distributed under the terms of this General Public License. The
	    &quot;Program&quot;, below, refers to any such program or work,
	    and a &quot;work based on the Program&quot; means either the
	    Program or any derivative work under copyright law: that is to
	    say, a work containing the Program or a portion of it, either
	    verbatim or with modifications and/or translated into another
	    language. (Hereinafter, translation is included without
	    limitation in the term &quot;modification&quot;.)  Each licensee
	    is addressed as &quot;you&quot;.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Activities other than copying, distribution and modification are
	    not covered by this License; they are outside its scope. The act
	    of running the Program is not restricted, and the output from
	    the Program is covered only if its contents constitute a work
	    based on the Program (independent of having been made by running
	    the Program). Whether that is true depends on what the Program
	    does.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You may copy and distribute verbatim copies of the Program's
	    source code as you receive it, in any medium, provided that you
	    conspicuously and appropriately publish on each copy an
	    appropriate copyright notice and disclaimer of warranty; keep 
	    intact all the notices that refer to this License and to the
	    absence of any warranty; and give any other recipients of the
	    Program a copy of this License along with the Program.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You may charge a fee for the physical act of transferring a copy,
	    and you may at your option offer warranty protection in exchange
	    for a fee.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You may modify your copy or copies of the Program or any portion
	    of it, thus forming a work based on the Program, and copy and
	    distribute such modifications or work under the terms of Section
	    1 above, provided that you also meet all of these conditions:
	  </para>
	  <orderedlist startingnumber="1" numeration="loweralpha">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		You must cause the modified files to carry prominent notices
		stating that you changed the files and the date of any change.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		You must cause any work that you distribute or publish, that
		in whole or in part contains or is derived from the Program
		or any part thereof, to be licensed as a whole at no charge
		to all third parties under the terms of this License.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		If the modified program normally reads commands interactively
		when run, you must cause it, when started running for such
		interactive use in the most ordinary way, to print or display
		an announcement including an appropriate copyright notice and a
		notice that there is no warranty (or else, saying that you
		provide a warranty) and that users may redistribute the
		program under these conditions, and telling the user how to
		view a copy of this License.  (Exception: if the Program
		itself is interactive but does not normally print such an
		announcement, your work based on the Program is not required
		to print an announcement.)
	      </para>
	      <para>
		These requirements apply to the modified work as a whole. If
		identifiable sections of that work are not derived from the
		Program, and can be reasonably considered independent and
		separate works in themselves, then this License, and its
		terms, do not apply to those sections when you distribute
		them as separate works.  But when you distribute the same
		sections as part of a whole which is a work based on the
		Program, the distribution of the whole must be on the terms
		of this License, whose permissions for other licensees extend
		to the entire whole, and thus to each and every part
		regardless of who wrote it.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		Thus, it is not the intent of this section to claim rights
		or contest your rights to work written entirely by you;
		rather, the intent is to exercise the right to control the
		distribution of derivative or collective works based on the
		Program.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		In addition, mere aggregation of another work not based on
		the Program with the Program (or with a work based on the
		Program) on a volume of a storage or distribution medium
		does not bring the other work under the scope of this License.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You may copy and distribute the Program (or a work based on it,
	    under Section 2) in object code or executable form under the
	    terms of Sections 1 and 2 above provided that you also do one
	    of the following:
	  </para>
	  <orderedlist startingnumber="1" numeration="loweralpha">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Accompany it with the complete corresponding machine-readable
		source code, which must be distributed under the terms of
		Sections 1 and 2 above on a medium customarily used for
		software interchange; or,
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Accompany it with a written offer, valid for at least three
		years, to give any third party, for a charge no more than your
		cost of physically performing source distribution, a complete
		machine-readable copy of the corresponding source code, to be
		distributed under the terms of Sections 1 and 2 above on a
		medium customarily used for software interchange; or,
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Accompany it with the information you received as to the offer
		to distribute corresponding source code.  (This alternative is
		allowed only for noncommercial distribution and only if you
		received the program in object code or executable form with such
		an offer, in accord with Subsection b above.)
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	  <para>
	    The source code for a work means the preferred form of the work
	    for making modifications to it.  For an executable work, complete
	    source code means all the source code for all modules it
	    contains, plus any associated interface definition files, plus the scripts used to control compilation and installation of the executable.
	    However, as a special exception, the source code distributed
	    need not include anything that is normally distributed (in
	    either source or binary form) with the major components
	    (compiler, kernel, and so on) of the operating system on which
	    the executable runs, unless that component itself accompanies
	    the executable.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If distribution of executable or object code is made by offering
	    access to copy from a designated place, then offering equivalent
	    access to copy the source code from the same place counts as
	    distribution of the source code, even though third parties are not
	    compelled to copy the source along with the object code.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Program
	    except as expressly provided under this License.  Any attempt
	    otherwise to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Program
	    is void, and will automatically terminate your rights under this
	    License. However, parties who have received copies, or rights,
	    from you under this License will not have their licenses
	    terminated so long as such parties remain in full compliance.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You are not required to accept this License, since you have not
	    signed it.  However, nothing else grants you permission to
	    modify or distribute the Program or its derivative works. These
	    actions are prohibited by law if you do not accept this License.
	    Therefore, by modifying or distributing the Program (or any work
	    based on the Program), you indicate your acceptance of this
	    License to do so, and all its terms and conditions for copying,
	    distributing or modifying the Program or works based on it.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Each time you redistribute the Program (or any work based on the
	    Program), the recipient automatically receives a license from
	    the original licensor to copy, distribute or modify the Program
	    subject to these terms and conditions.  You may not impose any
	    further restrictions on the recipients' exercise of the rights
	    granted herein. You are not responsible for enforcing compliance
	    by third parties to this License.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If, as a consequence of a court judgment or allegation of patent
	    infringement or for any other reason (not limited to patent
	    issues), conditions are imposed on you (whether by court order,
	    agreement or otherwise) that contradict the conditions of this
	    License, they do not excuse you from the conditions of this
	    License.  If you cannot distribute so as to satisfy
	    simultaneously your obligations under this License and any other
	    pertinent obligations, then as a consequence you may not
	    distribute the Program at all.  For example, if a patent license
	    would not permit royalty-free redistribution of the Program by
	    all those who receive copies directly or indirectly through you,
	    then the only way you could satisfy both it and this License
	    would be to refrain entirely from distribution of the Program.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If any portion of this section is held invalid or unenforceable
	    under any particular circumstance, the balance of the section is
	    intended to apply and the section as a whole is intended to
	    apply in other circumstances.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    It is not the purpose of this section to induce you to infringe
	    any patents or other property right claims or to contest
	    validity of any such claims; this section has the sole purpose
	    of protecting the integrity of the free software distribution
	    system, which is implemented by public license practices. Many
	    people have made generous contributions to the wide range of
	    software distributed through that system in reliance on
	    consistent application of that system; it is up to the
	    author/donor to decide if he or she is willing to distribute
	    software through any other system and a licensee cannot impose
	    that choice.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This section is intended to make thoroughly clear what is
	    believed to be a consequence of the rest of this License.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If the distribution and/or use of the Program is restricted in
	    certain countries either by patents or by copyrighted interfaces,
	    the original copyright holder who places the Program under this
	    License may add an explicit geographical distribution limitation
	    excluding those countries, so that distribution is permitted only
	    in or among countries not thus excluded.  In such case, this
	    License incorporates the limitation as if written in the body of
	    this License.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The Free Software Foundation may publish revised and/or new
	    versions of the General Public License from time to time.
	    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present
	    version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or
	    concerns.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Each version is given a distinguishing version number.  If the
	    Program specifies a version number of this License which applies
	    to it and "any later version", you have the option of following
	    the terms and conditions either of that version or of any later
	    version published by the Free Software Foundation. If the
	    Program does not specify a version number of this License, you
	    may choose any version ever published by the Free Software
	    Foundation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If you wish to incorporate parts of the Program into other free
	    programs whose distribution conditions are different, write to
	    the author to ask for permission.  For software which is
	    copyrighted by the Free Software Foundation, write to the Free
	    Software Foundation; we sometimes make exceptions for this. Our
	    decision will be guided by the two goals of preserving the free
	    status of all derivatives of our free software and of promoting
	    the sharing and reuse of software generally.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>NO WARRANTY</title>
      <orderedlist startingnumber="11" numeration="arabic">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    BECAUSE THE PROGRAM IS LICENSED FREE OF CHARGE, THERE IS NO
	    WARRANTY FOR THE PROGRAM, TO THE EXTENT PERMITTED BY APPLICABLE
	    LAW. EXCEPT WHEN OTHERWISE STATED IN WRITING THE COPYRIGHT
	    HOLDERS AND/OR OTHER PARTIES PROVIDE THE PROGRAM &quot;AS IS&quot;
	    WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED,
	    INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
	    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. THE ENTIRE
	    RISK AS TO THE QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THE PROGRAM IS WITH YOU.
	    SHOULD THE PROGRAM PROVE DEFECTIVE, YOU ASSUME THE COST OF ALL
	    NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    IN NO EVENT UNLESS REQUIRED BY APPLICABLE LAW OR AGREED TO IN
	    WRITING WILL ANY COPYRIGHT HOLDER, OR ANY OTHER PARTY WHO MAY
	    MODIFY AND/OR REDISTRIBUTE THE PROGRAM AS PERMITTED ABOVE, BE
	    LIABLE TO YOU FOR DAMAGES, INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL,
	    INCIDENTAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF THE USE OR
	    INABILITY TO USE THE PROGRAM (INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO LOSS
	    OF DATA OR DATA BEING RENDERED INACCURATE OR LOSSES SUSTAINED BY
	    YOU OR THIRD PARTIES OR A FAILURE OF THE PROGRAM TO OPERATE WITH
	    ANY OTHER PROGRAMS), EVEN IF SUCH HOLDER OR OTHER PARTY HAS BEEN
	    ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS</title>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>How to Apply These Terms to Your New Programs</title>
    <para>
       If you develop a new program, and you want it to be of the greatest
       possible use to the public, the best way to achieve this is to make
       it free software which everyone can redistribute and change under
       these terms.
    </para>
    <para>
      To do so, attach the following notices to the program.  It is safest
      to attach them to the start of each source file to most effectively
      convey the exclusion of warranty; and each file should have at least
      the "copyright" line and a pointer to where the full notice is found.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <para>
	<literallayout>
	  &lt;one line to give the program's name and a brief idea of what it does.&gt;
	  Copyright (C) &lt;year&gt;  &lt;name of author&gt;
	</literallayout>
      </para>
      <para>
	This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
	it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
	(at your option) any later version.
      </para>
      <para>
	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
	GNU General Public License for more details.
      </para>
      <para>
	You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
	Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307
	USA
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <para>
      Also add information on how to contact you by electronic and paper mail.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the program is interactive, make it output a short notice like this
      when it starts in an interactive mode:
    </para>
    <para>
      <literallayout>
	Gnomovision version 69, Copyright (C) year  name of author
	Gnomovision comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY; for details type `show w'.
	This is free software, and you are welcome to redistribute it
under certain conditions; type `show c' for details.
      </literallayout>
    </para>
    <para>
      The hypothetical commands `show w' and `show c' should show the
      appropriate parts of the General Public License.  Of course, the
      commands you use may be called something other than `show w' and
      `show c'; they could even be mouse-clicks or menu items --whatever
      suits your program.
    </para>
    <para>
      You should also get your employer (if you work as a programmer) or
      your school, if any, to sign a "copyright disclaimer" for the program,
      if necessary.  Here is a sample; alter the names:
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <para>
	Yoyodyne, Inc., hereby disclaims all copyright interest in the program
	`Gnomovision' (which makes passes at compilers) written by James Hacker.
      </para>
      <literallayout>
	&lt;signature of Ty Coon&gt;, 1 April 1989
	Ty Coon, President of Vice
      </literallayout>
    </sect2>
    <para>
      This General Public License does not permit incorporating your
      program into proprietary programs.  If your program is a subroutine
      library, you may consider it more useful to permit linking proprietary
      applications with the library.  If this is what you want to do, use
      the GNU Library General Public License instead of this License.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
<!--
<index>
</index>
-->
</book>

<!--
<structure xml:id="manual">
  <output renderas="book"/>
</structure>
-->
