<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="chapter.rdcatch">
  <title>Automating Tasks with RDCatch</title>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.automating_tasks_with_rdcatch">
    <title>Choosing the Correct Automation Tool</title>
    <para>
      Rivendell includes two modules specially optimized for performing
      automatic operations: the RDCatch and RDAirPlay modules. However,
      these two
      modules take radically different approaches in how they go about
      organizing and controlling operations, so a few words regarding
      each may be in order here.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDCatch is aimed at executing actions on the basis of a strict
      time-based schedule, referred to as an event list.  Each action
      (which can be a <emphasis>recording</emphasis>, a
      <emphasis>play out</emphasis>, an
      <emphasis>upload</emphasis> or <emphasis>download</emphasis>,
      a <emphasis>macro</emphasis> execution or an operation on an audio
      <emphasis>switcher</emphasis> device) executes on
      the basis of its scheduled time in the event list, independently of
      all other actions.  As such, RDCatch is often best suited for use in
      settings such as network head end operations or 'auxiliary' roles at
      broadcast stations, where the transitions between events are 
      generally not an important part of the presentation.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDAirPlay takes a very different approach, in that most events are
      organized into one or more playlists or logs. A Rivendell log is a
      list of one or more carts, organized in chronological order.  As the
      name implies, RDAirPlay is optimized for use in situations where the
      transitions between the various program elements are a key part of
      the delivery and presentation of the content, such as in live air
      play environments.
    </para>
    <para>
      Of course, it's entirely possible to use both modules, even together
      on the same machine at the same time – the Linux OS makes for a very
      robust and capable multitasking system. In this chapter, we will
      take a look at the capabilities of RDCatch.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.the_rdcatch_main_window">
    <title>The RDCatch Main Window</title>
    <para>
      After starting up RDCatch, you will see the
      <xref endterm="para.rdcatch.the_rdcatch_main_window" endlink="mediaobject.rdcatch.rdcatch_screenshot"/>. The window consists of four
      areas:  the record / play out decks at the top, the filter areas just
      below the decks, the events list and the audition buttons and other
      buttons at the bottom. We'll cover each of these in turn.
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.the_record___play_out_deck_area">
      <title>The Record / Play Out Deck Area</title>
      <para>
	If the system administrator has configured one or more RDCatch
	record or play out decks, they will be visible at the top of the
	RDCatch main window.  A record deck is a virtual 'recorder' that
	can be used to make automated recordings, while a play out deck
	can be used to automatically play out audio. It does not matter
	on which particular host a particular deck resides – all
	Rivendell decks throughout the system are visible in RDCatch,
	regardless of which host it is run upon.
      </para>
      <para>
	Starting at the left-hand edge of each deck, there is the deck's
	name, consisting of the name of the deck's host machine followed
	by a number and a letter, an <computeroutput>R</computeroutput>
	to indicate a record deck and a
	<computeroutput>P</computeroutput> to indicate a play out deck.
	Next, for record decks, there is
	a <computeroutput>MON</computeroutput> button, used to monitor the
	audio present at the deck input,
	followed by an <computeroutput>ABORT</computeroutput> button, used
	to manually stop an event
	running in the deck.  A description of the currently running event
	next appears (this area will be blank if no event is currently
	active), followed by the deck's status, which could be any of the 
	values in <xref linkend="table.rdcatch.rdcatch_event_states"/>.
    </para>
    <table xml:id="table.rdcatch.rdcatch_event_states" frame="all">
      <title>RDCatch Event States</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	<colspec colname="Status" />
	<colspec colname="Meaning" />
	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      Status
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Meaning
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      IDLE
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is available for events
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      READY
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck has started monitoring audio but the transport is
	      not yet rolling (record decks only).
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      WAITING
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is waiting for a GPI event (record decks only)
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      RECORDING
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is recording (record decks only)
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      PLAYING
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is playing out (play out decks only)
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      OFFLINE
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      The deck is configured but not available
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
      <para>
	<mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdcatch.rdcatch_screenshot">
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.rdcatch_screenshot.png" scale="45"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para xml:id="para.rdcatch.the_rdcatch_main_window">The RDCatch Main Window</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
    <para>
      Finally, each deck has an audio meter on its right-hand end, used
      to verify audio levels in realtime.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.the_filter_area">
      <title>The Filter Area</title>
      <para>
	Immediately below the decks is the filter area, consisting of the
	<computeroutput>Show Only Active Events</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>Show Only Today's Events</computeroutput>
	<computeroutput>Show DayOfWeek</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Show Event Type</computeroutput>
	controls, which are used to select which events will be
	visible in the events list area immediately below.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.the_event_list">
      <title>The Event List</title>
      <para>
	The event list is a system wide list of all events to be executed
	by RDCatch on all of the various hosts on the Rivendell network,
	with each event occupying a single line.  The status of each event
	is indicated by its background color, as shown in
	<xref linkend="table.rdcatch.rdcatch_event_state_colors"/>
      </para>
      <table xml:id="table.rdcatch.rdcatch_event_state_colors" frame="all">
	<title>RDCatch Event State Colors</title>
	<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colname="Color" />
	  <colspec colname="Meaning" />
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Color
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Meaning
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		YELLOW
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is next to be executed.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		GREEN
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is active.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		CYAN
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is in the READY state.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		VIOLET
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is in the WAITING state.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		RED/PINK
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		The event is reporting an error.
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	Each entry in the event list starts with an icon that indicates
	the type of the event, as shown in
	<xref linkend="table.rdcatch.rdcatch_event_icons"/>
      </para>
      <table xml:id="table.rdcatch.rdcatch_event_icons" frame="all">
	<title>RDCatch Event Icons</title>
	<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colname="Color" />
	  <colspec colname="Meaning" />
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[RECORD_ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Record Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[PLAYOUT ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Play Out Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[SWITCH ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Switch Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[MACRO ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Macro Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[UPLOAD ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Upload Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		[DOWNLOAD ICON]
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Download Event
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	Next on each line comes the
	<computeroutput>Description</computeroutput> (settable by the user) and
	<computeroutput>Location</computeroutput> for the event, the
	location being the name of the host/deck
	where the event will run. Then comes the
	<computeroutput>Start</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>End</computeroutput> parameters.
	These time-based parameters come in one of three different forms:
	a hard time, which is simply an absolute time (in twenty-four hour
	'military' format), a length (in HH:MM format, relative to an
	earlier start time), or a GPI start.  The GPI parameters can be
	somewhat involved.  They are specified in the following format:
      </para>
      <para>
	Gpi: &lt;start-time&gt;,&lt;end-time&gt;,&lt;gpi-num&gt;,&lt;wait-time&gt;
      </para>
      <para>
	Where:
      </para>
      <para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;start-time&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The time, in HH:MM:SS format, when RDCatch will start looking
		for a GPI event (also sometimes referred to as the window
		start time).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;end-time&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The time, in HH:MM:SS format, when RDCatch will stop looking
		for a GPI event (also sometime referred to as the window end
		time). 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;gpi-num&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The number of the GPI event to wait for, in the format
		MATRIX:LINE.  We will deal with GPI matrix and line numbers
		in detail when we cover RDAdmin.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>&lt;wait-time&gt;</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The amount of time to wait, in MM:SS format, between the
		reception of the GPI event and the actual start of the event
		(used only for Start parameters).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>
	For example, the start parameter 'Gpi: 14:00:00,14:05:59,0:1,01:00'
	has a window start time of 14:00:00 [2:00:00 PM], a window end time
	of 14:05:59, looks for a GPI event on line 0:1 and will wait one
	minute [01:00] after receiving the GPI before starting the event.
      </para>
      <para>
	Next come the <computeroutput>Source</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Destination</computeroutput> fields.
	The uses of these will
	vary depending upon what type of event is being listed, but should
	normally be fairly self-evident. For example, for a record event,
	the source field indicates the audio source from which the recording
	is to be made, while the destination indicates the cat/cut combo to
	which the recording should be made. Some events may leave one or the
	other of these fields blank.
      </para>
      <para>
	Now come the day of the week fields. These indicate on which days
	of the week the listed event should be executed, followed by the
	<computeroutput>Origin</computeroutput> field, which is simply a
	readout of the Origin data of the
	events underlying cut. There are a number of other fields which
	follow, but these are less important for understanding the
	operation of RDCatch.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch_the_button_area">
      <title>The Button Area</title>
      <para>
	At the bottom of the main window are various buttons. On the
	left-hand side, the <computeroutput>Add</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Delete</computeroutput> buttons are used to manage
	events in the event list. Clicking the
	<computeroutput>Scroll</computeroutput> button toggles
	RDCatch into and out of 'scroll mode'. In this mode, the event
	list display will be advanced automatically so as to keep the first
	actively running event centered within the event list area.
      </para>
      <para>
	On the right hand side, in addition to
	<computeroutput>Close</computeroutput>, are three audition
	buttons. These buttons can be used to audition the head and tail
	of each cut referenced by an event, thus making it possible to
	quickly verify that a set of automatic recordings were properly
	executed.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.adding_new_events">
    <title>Adding New Events</title>
    <para>
      A new event can be added to the event list by simply clicking the
      <computeroutput>Add</computeroutput> button to bring up the Add
      Event Dialog (see <xref endterm="para.the_add_event_dialog" endlinl="mediaobject.rdcatch.add_event_dialog"/>).
      Simply clicking the button that correspond to the desired type of
      event will create it.
    </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdcatch.add_event_dialog">
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.add_event_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para xml:id="para.the_add_event_dialog">The Add Event Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.automating_recordings">
    <title>Automating Recordings</title>
    <para>
      Automated recordings are configured by means of the Edit Recording
      dialog (see <xref endterm="the_edit_recording_dialog" endlink="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_recording_dialog"/>), which can be accessed either by clicking
      the <computeroutput>Recording</computeroutput> button in the Add Event
      dialog to create a new record
      event or by touching the <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button
      to modify an existing event.
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.the__start_parameters__section">
      <title>The 'Start Parameters' Section</title>
      <para>
	The start parameters of each recording are configured in the
	'Start Parameters' section.  A recording can be programmed to start
	on the basis of the wall clock time, referred to the hard start
	time, or upon reception of a general-purpose input, or GPI event
	originated by a satellite receiver, tone decoder or other external
	device. Programming a hard start time is merely a matter of
	entering the desired start time, in 24 hour 'military' format.
	Programming a GPI start involves, in addition to entry of the GPI
	parameters themselves (matrix and GPI line numbers) that
	<computeroutput>Window Start</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Windows End</computeroutput> times be entered,
	that define the 'window'
	during which reception of  the appropriate GPI event will be
	'recognized' by RDCatch. It is also optionally possible to specify
	a <computeroutput>Start Delay</computeroutput> between reception of
	the GPI event and the actual start of the recording.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_recording_dialog">
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.edit_recording_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para xml:id="the_edit_recording_dialog">The Edit Recording Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch_the__end_parameters__section">
      <title>The 'End Parameters' Section</title>
      <para>
	The end parameters of each recording are configured in the
	'End Parameters' section. A recording can be programmed to end on
	the basis of a hard time, its absolute length or in response to a
	GPI event. Programming of the
	<computeroutput>Hard Time</computeroutput> and 
	<computeroutput>Length</computeroutput> parameters
	should be fairly self-explanatory, while the parameters needed to
	program a GPI event are similar to those used for the start
	parameters, with the exception of the
	<computeroutput>Max Record Length</computeroutput> setting,
	which limits the maximum length of the recording in the event that
	the expected GPI event is never received.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.programming_multiple_recordings_in_a_single_event">
      <title>Programming Multiple Recordings in a Single Event</title>
      <para>
	If a record event is configured to use GPI for its start and Length
	or GPI for its end parameter, then it is possible to configure the
	event to make repeated, multiple recordings within a single event
	by checking the
	<computeroutput>Allow Multiple Recordings Within This Window</computeroutput>
	box in the 'Start Parameters' section. This can significantly reduce
	the amount of required record events when capturing material with
	high on-air turnover, such as newscasts or traffic reports.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.selecting_a_record_source">
      <title>Selecting a Record Source</title>
      <para>
	If the selected record deck (chosen in the
	<computeroutput>Location</computeroutput> drop-down menu
	at the top of the dialog) as been configured to operate with an
	audio switcher device, the appropriate audio input can be chosen
	from the <computeroutput>Source</computeroutput> drop-down menu.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.selecting_a_record_destination">
      <title>Selecting a Record Destination</title>
      <para>
	Each programmed recording must have a 'destination', a designated
	Cart/Cut which will hold the audio.  The currently programmed
	destination is shown in the Destination field, and can be changed
	by clicking the <computeroutput>Select</computeroutput> button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.setting_the_active_days_for_a_recording">
      <title>Setting the Active Days for a Recording</title>
      <para>
	A check should be placed next to each day of the week for which a
	recording should be made in the
	<computeroutput>Active Days</computeroutput> box.  If no days are
	checked, then no recordings at all will be made. 
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.record_list_management_with_event_active_and_make_oneshot">
      <title>Record List Management with Event Active and Make OneShot</title>
      <para>
	The record event will be actually executed only if
	<computeroutput>Event Active</computeroutput> check box
	(in the upper left corner of the dialog box) is ticked. By
	clearing this box, it's possible to 'bank' a record event without
	actually having it run, useful for events that are only used
	sporadically.
      </para>
      <para>
	For events that need to be executed only once, the
	<computeroutput>Make OneShot</computeroutput>
	box can be ticked. Such an event will execute just once, and
	then automatically delete itself from the event list.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.automating_playouts">
    <title>Automating Playouts</title>
    <para>
      Automated playouts are configured by means of the Edit Playout
      dialog (see <xref endterm="the_edit_playout_dialog" endlink="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_playout_dialog"/>), which can be accessed either by
      clicking the <computeroutput>Playout</computeroutput> button in
      the Add Event dialog to create a new
      record event or by touching the
      <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button to modify an existing
      event. The process of configuring a playout is very similar to that
      for configuring a recording – see the
      <xref linkend="sect.rdcatch.automating_recordings"/>
      above for details.
    </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_playout_dialog">
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.edit_playout_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para xml:id="the_edit_playout_dialog">The Edit Playout Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.automating_uploads_downloads">
    <title>Automating Uploads/Downloads</title>
    <para>
      It's possible to use RDCatch to automatically upload and download
      material from both local and Internet-based servers. Automated
      downloads are configured by means of the Edit Download dialog, which
      can be accessed either by clicking the
      <computeroutput>Download</computeroutput> button in the Add
      Event dialog (see <xref endterm="para.rdcatch.the_edit_download_dialog" endlink="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_download_dialog"/>) to create a new record event or
      by touching the <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button to
      modify an existing event.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_download_dialog">
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.edit_download_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para xml:id="para.rdcatch.the_edit_download_dialog">The Edit Download Dialog</para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      With the exception of the <computeroutput>Url</computeroutput>,
      <computeroutput>Username</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>Password</computeroutput> controls,
      the process of configuring a download is very similar to that for
      configuring a recording – see the
      <xref linkend="sect.rdcatch.automating_recordings"/> above for
      details.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <computeroutput>Url</computeroutput> control is used to specify
      the Uniform Resource Locater for
      the material to be downloaded. The following download types are
      supported: <userinput>http:</userinput>,
      <userinput>ftp:</userinput>, <userinput>sftp:</userinput> and
      <userinput>file:</userinput>. The <computeroutput>Url</computeroutput>
      field can also include
      wildcard characters that can be used to construct date-based URLs.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <computeroutput>Username</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>Password</computeroutput> fields are used to
      indicate the username
      and password required for access to the server referenced in the
      <computeroutput>Url</computeroutput>.
      For public web pages and anonymous FTP servers, these fields can be
      left blank.
    </para>
    <para>
      Automated uploads are configured by means of the Edit Upload dialog
      (see <xref endterm="para.rdcatch.the_edit_upload_dialog" endlink="metaobject.rdcatch.edit_upload_dialog"/>), which can be accessed either by clicking the
      <computeroutput>Upload</computeroutput> button in the Add Event
      dialog to create a new record event or
      by touching the <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button to
      modify an existing event. The
      following upload types are supported: <userinput>ftp:</userinput>,
      <userinput>sftp:</userinput> and <userinput>file:</userinput>.  As with
      downloads, the <computeroutput>Url</computeroutput> field can also
      include wildcard characters that
      can be used to construct date-based URLs.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject xml:id="metaobject.rdcatch.edit_upload_dialog">
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.edit_upload_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para xml:id="para.rdcatch.the_edit_upload_dialog">The Edit Upload Dialog</para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      Configuration of an upload event is very similar to that of a download,
      with the addition of the
      <computeroutput>Export Format</computeroutput> control.
      This is used to set
      what file format should be used for the upload. Depending upon what
      software encoders have been installed by the system administrator,
      the following export types may be available: 
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  PCM16 Linear (*.wav)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  Free Lossless Audio Codec [FLAC] (*.flac)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  MPEG Layer 2 (*.mp2)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  MPEG Layer 3 (*.mp3)
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  OggVorbis (*.ogg)
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The desired upload format and parameters are set by clicking the
      <computeroutput>Set</computeroutput> button.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch_automating_macro_execution">
    <title>Automating Macro Execution</title>
    <para>
      It's possible to configure the automatic execution of a Macro Cart
      by means of the Edit Cart Event dialog (see <xref endterm="para.rdcatch.the_edit_cart_event_dialog" endlink="mediaobject.dcatch.edit_cart_event_dialog"/>), which
      can be accessed either by clicking the
      <computeroutput>Macro Cart</computeroutput> button in the Add
      Event dialog to create a new Macro Cart event or by touching the
      <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button to modify an existing
      event.  The process of configuring
      a macro cart event is very similar to that for configuring a
      recording – see <xref linkend="sect.rdcatch.automating_recordings"/>
      above for details.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.dcatch.edit_cart_event_dialog">
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.edit_cart_event_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para xml:id="para.rdcatch.the_edit_cart_event_dialog">The Edit Cart Event Dialog</para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdcatch.automating_switcher_operations">
    <title>Automating Switcher Operations</title>
    <para>
      It's possible to configure an automatic operation on a switcher
      device by means of the Edit Switcher Event dialog (see 
      <xref endterm="para.rdcatch.the_edit_switcher_event_dialog" endlink="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_switcher_event_dialog"/>), which can be accessed either by clicking the
      <computeroutput>Switch Event</computeroutput> button
      in the Add Event dialog to create a new switch event or by touching
      the <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button to modify an
      existing event.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdcatch.edit_switcher_event_dialog">
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdcatch.edit_switcher_event_dialog.png" scale="50"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para xml:id="para.rdcatch.the_edit_switcher_event_dialog">The Edit Switcher Event Dialog</para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to the usual fields, a switch event has
      <computeroutput>Switch Matrix</computeroutput>
      (the name of one of the switch matrices associated with the selected
      <computeroutput>Location</computeroutput>),
      <computeroutput>Switch Input</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>Switch Output</computeroutput> controls.
      When executed, a
      switch events causes a take operation to be performed on the specified
      switcher device between the specified input and output.  It is
      possible to specify the input and output either by their alphanumeric
      names (assigned in RDAdmin) or by their absolute numbers.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
