<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="chapter.rdlogin">
  <title>Managing the Current User with RDLogin</title>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogin.managing_the_current_user_with_rdlogin">
    <title>RDLogin</title>
    <para>
      Rivendell uses a sophisticated system of user privileges to keep track
      of which users have permission to perform what operations.
      These privileges are tracked by the system on the basis of
      <emphasis>user accounts</emphasis>.
      Creating user accounts and administering their permissions
      are done in the RDAdmin module and are covered in
      <xref linkend="sect.rdadmin.managing_users" />.
    </para>
    <para>
      It's important to note that these user accounts are
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> the same
      thing as the “Login Name” that is used to log into the computer system
      itself. Rather, they exist and have meaning only within the Rivendell
      system. For the rest of this discussion, when we talk about “users”,
      it is these “Rivendell users” that we are referring to.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each Rivendell host has a default user. As the name implies, this is
      the user that is automatically logged in after the system is booted.
      By default, the name of this user is “user”, but the system
      administrator may have changed this to some other name.
    </para>
    <para>
      For many sites, a single default user is all that is ever required.
      For some sites however, particularly larger ones, it is desirable
      to have multiple user accounts, each tailored to a particular person
      or “role”, with privileges assigned appropriately.  Such sites
      require a means to log different users in and out of the system
      without interfering with any playout operations that may be ongoing
      at the time.  RDLogin is the module for doing this.
    </para>
    <para>
      RDLogin will display a small window after being started, showing the
      currently logged-in user. To change to a
      different user, select the desired user name from the Username:
      control, enter the correct password, and then touch the Set User
      button.  To “log out” of the system (in reality, just return to the
      default user), simply touch the Default User button (no password is
      required to set the default user).  To exit RDLogin and do nothing,
      simply touch the Cancel button.
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogin.rdlogin_screenshot.png" scale="70"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <note>
      The system administrator may have configured the system so as not to
      display the list of available users. If this is the case, you will
      need to enter the username of the user to log in rather than selecting
      it from a dropdown list.
    </note>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
