<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="chapter.rdlogedit">
  <title>Generating and Maintaining Logs with RDLogEdit</title>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.logs_and_log_events">
    <title>Logs and Log Events</title>
    <para>
      A Rivendell log is a sequence of one or more events to be executed by
      the system, arranged in chronological order. (This functionality is
      sometimes referred to as a playlist in other automation systems).
      Several different types of events can be included in a log, along
      with parameters governing how and under what circumstances they will
      be executed.
    </para>
    <para>
      Upon startup, RDLogEdit will show the current list of all logs on the
      system. A number of important attributes of
      logs can be seen from <xref endterm="para.rdlogedit.the_rdlogedit_main_window" endlink="mediaobject.rdlogedit.rdlogedit_screenshot"/>, the first being the log
      name, with a summary status indicator next to it. The name is an
      alpha-numeric label that is used as a unique “handle” by the system
      to reference each log, and can be up to a maximum of 64 characters
      long. The status indicator is intended as a quick visual guide as
      to whether a particular log is ready for air (green check mark) or
      not (red ex). 
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject xml:id="mediaobject.rdlogedit.rdlogedit_screenshot">
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.rdlogedit_screenshot.png" scale="65"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para xml:id="para.rdlogedit.the_rdlogedit_main_window">The RDLogEdit Main Window</para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes the log's unique <computeroutput>Name</computeroutput>,
      assigned at the time the log was created, followed by it's
      <computeroutput>Description</computeroutput>.
      This is a free-form alpha-numeric
      label that can be used to record any information that might be useful
      to have appear on the log list (e.g. “This log for Sunday's show, don't
      modify!”).
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes a column showing the owning
      <computeroutput>Service</computeroutput>. Each log is owned
      by exactly one service, which determines under what circumstances
      the log can be played and where electronic log reconciliation (ELR)
      data resulting from log playouts is sent (for an overview of
      Rivendell services, see <xref linkend="sect.overview.services"/>).
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes three “status indicator” columns
      (<computeroutput>Music</computeroutput>,
      <computeroutput>Traffic</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>Tracks</computeroutput>) indicating the log's
      degree of readiness for air. A red indicator indicates that the
      particular data element is required but currently missing, a green
      indicator indicates an element is required and present, while a
      white indicator indicates that an element is not required.
      Additionally, the <computeroutput>TRACKS</computeroutput> column
      contains a pair of numbers
      indicating how many completed voice tracks exist in the log versus
      how many total track markers exist (the subject of voice tracks and
      track markers will be covered in more detail below). When all three
      of these status indicators show either green or white, the summary
      status indicator (at the beginning of the log's entry in the list)
      will show as a green check mark, while a red indicator in any of
      these three fields will show a red ex. (NOTE: because a log sports
      a red ex does not indicate that the respective log cannot be played.
      It is merely a visual indicator to allow logs to be quickly
      &quot;eyeballed&quot; for completeness).
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes a pair of columns indicating the valid start date and end
      date for the log.
    </para>
    <para>
      Next comes an <computeroutput>Auto Refresh</computeroutput> column
      that indicates whether the log has auto refresh enabled. (For a
      discussion of auto refresh, see FIXME).
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, there are &quot;datestamp&quot; columns, indicating 
      date/time of the log's <computeroutput>Origin</computeroutput>,
      <computeroutput>Last Linked</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>Last Modified</computeroutput> operation.
    </para>
    <para>
      A report that lists the available logs on the system can be generated
      by touching the <computeroutput>Log Report</computeroutput> button.
    </para>
    <para>
      A new log can be created by touching the
      <computeroutput>Add</computeroutput> button and entering a
      name, or an existing log inspected and modified by touching its entry
      on the log list and then touching the
      <computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput> button, resulting in the
      log being opened in the Edit Log dialog.
      The Edit Log dialog consists of three parts: the top section, where
      much of the information shown on the log list can be inspected and
      modified; the middle section, which shows the list of events
      comprising the log, and the bottom section, where buttons for
      modifying and saving the log are located. Each event in a log can
      be one of several different types, indicated by the icon displayed
      at the start of the line (see
      <xref linkend="table.rdlogedit.log_event_type_icons"/> for a
      breakdown of the various icons).
    </para>
    <para>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.edit_log_dialog.png" scale="55"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>The Edit Log Dialog</para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      The following types of events can be incorporated into a
      Rivendell log:
    </para>
    <table xml:id="table.rdlogedit.log_event_type_icons" frame="all" pgwide="0">
      <title>Log Event Type Icons</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	<colspec colname="Icon" colwidth="1.0*"/>
	<colspec colname="Meaning" colwidth="10.0*"/>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/play.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Audio Cart
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/track_cart.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Voice Track Audio Cart
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/rml5.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Macro Cart
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/notemarker.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Note Marker
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/mic16.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Track Marker
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/chain.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Chain Event
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/music.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Music Import Link
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">
	      <inlinemediaobject>
		<imageobject>
		  <imagedata fileref="../../icons/traffic.png" scale="100"/>
		</imageobject>
	      </inlinemediaobject>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Traffic Import Link
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.audio_carts">
      <title>Audio Carts</title>
      <para>
	The first, and usually most common type of log event is an audio cart.
	As the name implies, audio carts are Library entries that contain
	audio material intended for playout. Audio carts were covered in
	detail in <xref linkend="chapter.rdlibrary"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.macro_carts">
      <title>Macro Carts</title>
      <para>
	A macro cart is a cart from the Library that contains one or more
	system commands that can be used to cause the system to take various
	actions.  They were touched upon in
	<xref linkend="chapter.rdlibrary"/>, and will be discussed in detail
	in <xref linkend="chapter.rml"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.note_markers">
      <title>Note Markers</title>
      <para>
	A note marker is an entry in the log that contains text intended to
	be seen by operators and used as a guide or reminder (program coders
	sometimes refer to this sort of functionality as a
	<emphasis>remark</emphasis> or <emphasis>comment</emphasis>,
	as seen in the <code>REM</code> command used by BASIC programmers).
	Note markers
	belong to a class of log events known as meta events because (unlike
	carts, which exist in the Library independently of whether they are
	placed in a log or not), they have no independent existence outside
	of the specific log where they are placed. A note marker has
	absolutely no effect on the execution of a log other than to simply
	display some text at a specified point in a log, and as such can be
	useful as a mechanism for making notes or reminders to oneself or
	to others who may be executing the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.track_markers">
      <title>Track Markers</title>
      <para>
	A track marker is another meta event that is very similar in operation
	to note markers, with one key addition: track markers designate or
	&quot;bookmark&quot; a place in the log where a voice track is to be
	recorded. (The entire topic of voice tracks and tracking will be
	covered in detail in <xref linkend="chapter.voicetracking"/>).
	As with note markers, track
	markers have absolutely no effect on the execution of a log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.chain_events">
      <title>Chain Events</title>
      <para>
	Each event in a log has a transition type, shown in the
	<computeroutput>Trans</computeroutput>
	column of the Edit Log dialog. The transition type determines what
	happens when one event in a log ends and the next starts. Three basic
	transition types can exist in a Rivendell log: 
	<computeroutput>PLAY</computeroutput>,
	<computeroutput>SEGUE</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>STOP</computeroutput>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.import_links">
      <title>Import Links</title>
      <para>
	An import link is a placeholder event that shows where events imported
	from the external music or traffic scheduling system will eventually
	go. They will be covered in detail in
	<xref linkend="chapter.rdlogmanager"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Each event in a Rivendell log can have its parameters modified by
	touching its entry in the Edit Log dialog and then clicking the
	<computeroutput>Edit</computeroutput>
	button, thus opening up the Edit Log Entry dialog, shown below.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.edit_log_entry_dialog.png" scale="55"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>The Edit Log Entry Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.edit_log_marker_dialog.png" scale="55"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>The Edit Log Marker Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.edit_voice_track_marker_dialog.png" scale="55"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>The Edit Voice Track Marker Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.edit_log_chain_dialog.png" scale="55"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>The Edit Log Chain Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.event_transitions">
    <title>Event Transitions</title>
    <para>
      Each event in a log has a transition type, shown in the
      <computeroutput>Trans</computeroutput>
      column of the Edit Log dialog. The transition type determines what
      happens when one event in a log ends and the next starts. Three basic
      transition types can exist in a Rivendell log:
      <computeroutput>PLAY</computeroutput>, 
      <computeroutput>SEGUE</computeroutput> and
      <computeroutput>STOP</computeroutput>.
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.the_play_transition">
      <title>The PLAY Transition</title>
      <para>
	If an event has a <computeroutput>PLAY</computeroutput> transition,
	then it will begin playing when
	the previous event has finished.
	<computeroutput>PLAY</computeroutput> transitions are used when
	automatic event sequencing is desired with no audio overlap (such
	as when playing two voice-only announcements back-to-back).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.the_segue_transition">
      <title>The SEGUE Transition</title>
      <para>
	<computeroutput>SEGUE</computeroutput> transitions are similar to
	<computeroutput>PLAY</computeroutput> transitions, with one key
	difference: if the finishing event contains segue data (either from
	the Library or from a custom transition programmed in the voice
	tracker), then the event will start before the prior event is
	finished, causing the two pieces of audio to overlap and mix together.
	<computeroutput>SEGUE</computeroutput> transitions can be a very
	powerful tool for creating a variety
	of special effects, particularly when used in conjunction with
	musical material.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.the_stop_transition">
      <title>The STOP Transition</title>
      <para>
	As the name implies, <computeroutput>STOP</computeroutput>
	transitions cause execution of the log to
	be suspended prior to execution of the event. This is often the
	desired behavior in situations where the log playout needs to be
	synchronized to one or more external audio sources (such as remote
	satellite feeds), and is commonly used in conjunction with Hard
	Timed events (see <xref linkend="sect.rdlogedit.time_and_time_types"/>).
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.time_and_time_types">
    <title>Time and Time Types</title>
    <para>
      All Rivendell log events have an associated time type, which controls
      what effect (if any) the passage of time will have on the event.
      There are two basic time types: <emphasis>relative</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>hard</emphasis>. Additionally,
      the hard time type has several additional options that further modify
      its behavior.
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.the_relative_time_type">
      <title>The Relative Time Type</title>
      <para>
	The default time type for log events, a relative time type simply
	means that the event is assumed to have a start time of whenever
	the previous event ends (if it has a
	<computeroutput>PLAY</computeroutput> or 
	<computeroutput>SEGUE</computeroutput> transition)
	or whenever it is started (if it has a 
	<computeroutput>STOP</computeroutput> transition).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.the_hard_time_type">
      <title>The Hard Time Type</title>
      <para>
	A hard time type causes the event to be executed or otherwise acted
	upon when the wall clock equals the time associated with the event.
	Hard times are a powerful feature that can be used to synchronize
	the log to various external events.  An event can be assigned a
	hard time by clicking the <computeroutput>Start at</computeroutput>
	check box in the Edit Log Entry
	and filling in the desired time, and will show up with the letter
	<computeroutput>T</computeroutput> appearing at the beginning of
	its listed time in the
	<computeroutput>Time</computeroutput> column of the Edit Log dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
	The specific action that is performed when the time matches is
	determined by the option parameters supplied as part of the event.
	Three basic actions are possible:
      </para>
      <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    Start the event immediately
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    Cue to the event (&quot;Make Next&quot;)
	  </listitem>1
	  <listitem>
	    Wait up to some period of time, then start the event
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <sect3 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.start_immediately">
	<title>Start Immediately</title>
	<para>
	  As implied by the name, if the event is set to start immediately,
	  it will be started as soon as the hard time is reached. Any
	  currently playing events in the log will be simultaneously
	  stopped down.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.cue_to_the_event___make_next___">
	<title>Cue to the Event (&quot;Make Next&quot;)</title>
	<para>
	  If set to 'Make Next', the event will be cued up to become the
	  next event to be executed in the log, bypassing any intervening
	  events in the log between the currently playing event and the
	  hard timed one.  Any currently playing events are unaffected.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.wait_up_to_some_period_of_time__then_start_the_event">
	<title>Wait up to some period of time, then start the event</title>
	<para>
	  Very similar to &quot;start immediately&quot;, with the
	  difference that, if one or more events are currently playing,
	  the log will wait up to the specified amount of time
	  before stopping them and starting the new event. If the currently
	  playing event(s) finish before the specified time period has elapsed,
	  then the event is started immediately.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.editing_log_event_parameters">
    <title>Editing Log Event Parameters</title>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.specifying_a_cart">
      <title>Specifying a Cart</title>
      <para>
	The cart number to use for an event can be specified by touching
	the <computeroutput>Select Cart</computeroutput> button in the
	Edit Log Entry dialog, which will
	open up the Select Cart dialog.
	Alternatively, it is possible to simply enter the cart number in
	the <computeroutput>Cart</computeroutput> field if the number is
	already known. The <computeroutput>Title</computeroutput> and
	<computeroutput>Artist</computeroutput> information will be
	supplied automatically by the system
	from the cart's label.
      </para>
      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="rdlogedit.select_cart_dialog.png" scale="55"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>The Select Cart Dialog</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.specifying_meta_event_parameters">
      <title>Specifying Meta Event Parameters</title>
      <para>
	Note marker and track marker events each take only a single
	parameter:  a <computeroutput>Comment</computeroutput> text that
	will show up on the log entry.
	In the case of a chain event, the name of the log to chain to must
	be supplied in the <computeroutput>Log Name</computeroutput> field,
	or the <computeroutput>Select</computeroutput> button can be
	touched to bring up the Select Log dialog to allow a name to picked
	from a list of all those available.  Note that meta events are
	assigned transition and time types just the same as cart events.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.rearranging_log_events">
      <title>Rearranging Log Events</title>
      <para>
	Existing events in a log can be cut, copied, pasted or rearranged
	by touching the appropriate buttons in the Edit Log dialog.
	In addition, touch the <computeroutput>Delete</computeroutput>
	button will cause the selected
	log event(s) to be removed from the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.saving_or_abandoning_changes_to_a_log">
      <title>Saving or Abandoning Changes to a Log</title>
      <para>
	Any changes made to a log can be saved by touching either the
	<computeroutput>Save</computeroutput>
	or <computeroutput>OK</computeroutput> buttons in the Edit Log
	dialog.  The current log can be saved
	under a different name by touching the
	<computeroutput>Save As</computeroutput> button, while
	touching <computeroutput>Cancel</computeroutput> will abandon
	any changes made since the last save.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.missing_invalid_cart_events">
      <title>Missing/Invalid Cart Events</title>
      <para>
	If a given event has a problem (such as referencing a cart that
	does not exist in the Library, or that is not enabled for play on
	the log's owning service) its entry will be highlighted either
	RED (indicating a missing/invalid cart) or MAGENTA (indicating a
	cart without permission to run on the owning service). It's also
	possible to generate an  exception report summarizing problem cart
	entries by touching the 
	<computeroutput>Check Log</computeroutput> button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.generating_log_reports">
    <title>Generating Log Reports</title>
    <para>
      Various Log reports can be generated by touching the
      <computeroutput>Reports</computeroutput> button
      on the Edit Log dialog and then selecting the desired report and
      touching the <computeroutput>Generate</computeroutput> button.
      The following reports are available:
    </para>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.log_listing">
      <title>Log Listing</title>
      <para>
	A chronological listing of all events in the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.log_exception_report">
      <title>Log Exception Report</title>
      <para>
	A list of missing/unplayable carts referenced in the log.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect.rdlogedit.auditioning_audio">
    <title>Auditioning Audio</title>
    <para>
      The audio referenced by an audio event can be sampled in the Edit
      Audio dialog by highlighting the desired event and then touching the
      <computeroutput>Play</computeroutput> button. No attempt to evaluate
      the rotation logic of the event
      is made – the audio played is intended solely as a 'sample' to help
      identify the type of material.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
