<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
<info>
  <title>Rivendell C Library API</title>
  <author>
    <personname>
      <firstname>Todd</firstname>
      <surname>Baker</surname>
      <email>bakert@rfa.org</email>
    </personname>
  </author>
</info>

<section>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>
    This is a C Library that can be used to access and query the Rivendell database.  These functions
    allow the programmer to access the Rivendell Web API components directly, and provides 
    almost complete 
    functionality in relation to content in an existing Rivendell system.  See function 
    descriptions for further information on using these functions below.
  </para>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Function Descriptions</title>
  <para>
  <command>RD_AudioInfo</command> This function returns
information about an entry in the audio store.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_AddCart</command> This function 
    adds a cart to a Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_AddCut</command> This function 
    adds a cut to a Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_AssignSchedCode</command> This function
    assigns a Scheduler Code to carts in a Rivendell database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_AudioStore</command> This function 
    returns information about the audio store.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_CopyAudio</command> This function 
    copys PCM/MPEG data from one Cart/Cut to another Cart/Cut.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_CreateTicket</command> This function 
    will create an Authentification ticket in the Rivendell database
    that can be used in leu of username/password pair.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_DeleteAudio</command> This function 
    deletes PCM/MPEG data from the audio store.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_EditCart</command> This function 
    edits the fields within a cart in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_EditCut</command> This function 
    edit the fields within a cut in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_Export</command> This function 
    exports PCM/MPEG data from the audio store.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ExportPeaks</command> This function 
    exports Peak Data from the audio store.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_Import</command> This function 
    imports PCM/MPEG data into the audio store.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListCart</command> This function 
    lists the fields within a cart in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListCarts</command> This function 
    lists the carts in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListCartSchedCodes</command> This function 
    lists the Scheduler Codes assigned to a cart in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListCut</command> This function 
    lists the fields within a cut in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListCuts</command> This function 
    lists the cuts that exist in a Cart entry.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListGroup</command> This function 
    lists the group field entries for a specific group in the Rivendell database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListGroups</command> This function 
    lists the groups within the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListLog</command> This function 
    lists the log lines for a particular log file within the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListLogs</command> This function 
    lists the Log Files within the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListSchedCodes</command> This function 
    lists the Scheduler Codes that currently exist in the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListServices</command> This function 
    lists the Servicess that are stored within the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_ListSystemSettings</command> This function 
    lists the System Settings that are stored within the Rivendell Database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_RemoveCart</command> This function 
    removes a cart from the Rivendell database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_RemoveCut</command> This function 
    removes a cut from the Rivendell database.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_TrimAudio</command> This function 
    returns a time pointer to the first and last instance of a particular dB level in a cut.
  </para>
  <para><command>RD_UnassignSchedCode</command> This function 
    unassigns a Scheduler Code from a cart in the Rivendell database.
  </para>
</section>
</article>
